<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The righteous mans euidences for heauen, or, A treatise shewing how euery one, while hee liues heere, may certainely know what shall become of him after his departure out of this life</title>
            <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1589-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 159 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S953</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23092263</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23092263</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26211</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26211)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1780:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The righteous mans euidences for heauen, or, A treatise shewing how euery one, while hee liues heere, may certainely know what shall become of him after his departure out of this life</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1589-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The sixt edition, corrected and inlarged /</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[20], 297 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Beale for Ed. Brewster, and are to be sold at the signe of the Star at the vvest end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹²(-A1,2) B-N¹² O⁵.</note>
                  <note>Page 295 misnumbered as 259.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn and cropped at top; lacking signature I1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heaven --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHTEOVS MANS Euidences for Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> A TREATISE SHEWING how euery one, while hee liues heere, may certainely know what <hi>ſhall become of him after his</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of this life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixt Edition, corrected and inlarged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tymothy Rogers,</hi> Preacher of Gods word in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 107.43.</bibl> Who is wiſe, that he may obſerue theſe things? for they ſhall vnderſtand the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe of the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 10.</bibl> Giue all diligence to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure: for if you doe theſe things yee ſhall neuer fall.</q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>I. Beale</hi> for <hi>Ed. Brewſter:</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the <hi>Star</hi> at the VVeſt end of Pauls. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHORS Apologie to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Arre was it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the firſt, Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader, thus to haue expoſed my ſelfe to the common view of men, but rather to haue hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:26211:3"/>
this my weake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception for euer, neuer to haue come to the birth: but when it would abide no longer, to bee impriſoned in the womb, but violently brake forth, I thought to deale wiſely with it, though not (as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi>) cruelly to murther it, yet at leaſt (as <hi>Moſes</hi> his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) charitably to hide it, for my own priuat vſe: or at the beſt to haue put it to Nurſe in an obſcure Country-village, where my ſelfe am Paſtor, to ſee the good vſage of it; for which end I be-truſted a
<pb facs="tcp:26211:3"/>
friend or two, for the printing of ſome few, copies, onely for my ſelfe: but through friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I was deceiued: for whereas I expected a ſmall number, like the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that went againſt <hi>Benhadad,</hi> like two little flocks of Kids: My bookes were ſent forth in multitudes, like the <hi>Aramites</hi> that fill'd the country. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.27. Onely this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, they came not forth againſt the hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the people of God, (as did the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi>) but rather to ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:26211:4"/>
on their ſide. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driuen to a ſtraight, (though that which is done, can not bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done) yet I thought it my part to doe what I could, namely, to mend, and inlarge that which is done; that ſeeing it muſt bee common, it may not be altogether vn-vſefull: Confeſſing ingenuouſly, I had rather it ſhould not haue bin common; eſpecially conſidering, that there are better bred and nobler borne Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of very worthy men, concerning this ſubiect; but thus it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:26211:4"/>
bee now: if therefore it may but ſerue as an hand-maid to theirs, ſo thou mayeſt reape ſome profit hereby, I haue both my deſire, and full contentment. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the bond of Faith and Loue, <hi>Timothy Rogers.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="counsel_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:5"/>
            <head>Councell to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N ſailing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Seas of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome world toward the heauenly land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> wee are to paſſe two dangerous rocks, the one called <hi>Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the other <hi>Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> happy is the man that eſcaping them both, ſhall make a ſafe arriuall
<pb facs="tcp:26211:6"/>
at the promiſed Land: Millions of Chriſtians in profeſsion are caſt away againſt the one, or againſt the other: for ſome, though they haue no true grace wrought in them, thinke notwithſtanding that they are in no danger, but ſhall certainly bee ſaued: which is as great preſumption, as if a man being ſtricken thorow the heart, ſhould thinke himſelfe very well, and in no danger of death. Others when they come to apprehend the heauy wrath of God, and deadly curſe of the Law due vnto them by nature for ſinne, in helliſh
<pb facs="tcp:26211:6"/>
ſorrow vtterly deſpaire, Some ſincere Chriſtians alſo there are, againſt whom the Tempter doth ſo far preuaile, that in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, they are ready to faint, for feare of hell and condemnation; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they cannot periſh, or ſuffer ſhipwrack againſt this rock of <hi>Deſperation,</hi> yet their poore Barke may bee ſo battered and beaten againſt it, as that peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they may bee a long while after in rigging and mending of it vp againe, with griefe and hart-ſmart that thou maiſt eſcape theſe
<pb facs="tcp:26211:7"/>
dangers, vſe theſe ſhort queſtions and anſweres as a Sea-mappe, or guide vnto thee, to ſhew thee thy way betweene both, that ſo thou mayeſt ſaile to Heauen in more ſafety, confidence, and comfort. Now to the end that the better vſe may bee made heereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeech thee of theſe things. Firſt, what multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes daily (departing this world) throng in at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall gates of Hell, for want of the aſſurance of their ſaluation. Secondly, conſider that thou being by nature a condemned man, if thy pardon be not ſealed
<pb facs="tcp:26211:7"/>
to thy conſcience, and giuen thee before the breath bee once out of thy body, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward though thou wouldeſt, or couldeſt giue a thouſand worlds for it, it cannot bee had: conſider againe of the vncertainty of thy life, thou canſt not tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt bee aliue to morrow, for <hi>thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not what a day may bring forth:</hi> Conſider al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the certainty of thy death: dye thou muſt, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſurer, for who can ſtand againſt the power thereof? and, oh how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the remembrance of death to one that is not
<pb facs="tcp:26211:8"/>
aſſured of his ſaluation! Further, conſider how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible the Iudgement day will bee to all ſuch as get not the aſſurance of their ſaluation in their life time: which may will they turne themſelues then? Oh what will they doe? Mountaines and Hills fall vpon vs, and cruſh vs in peeces, ſhall they cry, but it ſhall not bee. Then what moſt dolefull and intollerable torments ſhall they for euer endure in hell; able to breake the hardeſt heart to thinke on? Oh <hi>who ſhall dwell with the deuoring fire? who ſhall dwell with the
<pb facs="tcp:26211:8"/>
euerlaſting burning?</hi> Laſtly, conſider of the moſt ineſtimable ioyes of Heauen, and incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble delights, which all they ſhall haue, who get the aſſurance of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in this life: <hi>Such as eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, nor the heart of man concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of:</hi> O heauenly ioy! O ſweet delights! O excellent ſurmounting glory! O endleſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabounding pleaſures! wherewith their hearts ſhall bee rauiſhed and for-euer repleniſhed. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe conſiderations,
<pb facs="tcp:26211:9"/>
I earneſtly requeſt thee, if thou haſt any pittie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration on thy poore ſoule, <hi>Make thy calling and election ſure, euen while it is called to day:</hi> How ſhall I doe that, thou wilt ſay? This briefe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe will ſhew thee how, yea, more then that; heereby thou mayeſt bee aſſured of thy ſaluation, if thou vſe it rightly, but then thou muſt goe through it with good aduiſement; if thou touch the Honie-combe with thy lips, thou mayeſt finde ſweetnes; but if thou ſucke, much more: ſo read theſe things, as to learne
<pb facs="tcp:26211:9"/>
them, ſo learne, as to know thy owne eſtate thereby, ſo mighteſt thou ſucke out the hole ſweetneſſe thereof; get the true ſtamp of them in thy heart, ſo thou maieſt be ſure thou ſhalt be ſaued: which the Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen grant for his mercies ſake. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:10"/>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:11"/>
            <list>
               <head>A Treatiſe of ſaluation wherein are</head>
               <item>ſignes propounded
<list>
                     <item>prouing ſaluation,
<list>
                           <item>the mother grace, Faith. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>ſiſter-graces
<list>
                                 <item>more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,
<list>
                                       <item>Conuerſion p. 29</item>
                                       <item>Iuſtification. p. 36</item>
                                       <item>Adoption. p. 41</item>
                                       <item>Sanctification. p. 50</item>
                                       <item>Repentance. p. 61</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.
<list>
                                       <item>Knowledge. p. 77</item>
                                       <item>Hope. p. 86</item>
                                       <item>Loue of God. p. 95</item>
                                       <item>Loue of the godly p 104</item>
                                       <item>Feare of God. p. 115</item>
                                       <item>Ioy. p. 125</item>
                                       <item>Patience. p. 135</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>witneſſing ſaluation,
<list>
                           <item>Gods ſpirit.</item>
                           <item>Gods word.
<list>
                                 <item>Pſal. 34.8. p. 155</item>
                                 <item>Reu. 21.6. p. 159</item>
                                 <item>Math. 5.3, 4. p. 163</item>
                                 <item>Rom. 10.13. p. 167</item>
                                 <item>Reu. 3.21. p. 172</item>
                                 <item>2. Tim. 2.21. p. 179</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Doubts reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<list>
                     <item>Election. p. 196</item>
                     <item>VVeaknes in Grace. p. 201</item>
                     <item>Greatnes of ſinne. p. 211</item>
                     <item>Hypocriſie. p. 221</item>
                     <item>Perſeuerance. p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3</item>
                     <item>Preſuming. p. 238</item>
                     <item>Euill thoughts. p. 243</item>
                     <item>Afflictions. p. 252</item>
                     <item>Feare of death. p. 278</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26211:11"/>
            <head>The Righteous Mans Euidence <hi>for Heauen.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſerues vs thus fitly (my Chriſtian friend) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a while together, and ſeeing there is no conference ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table or profitable as that which is about the affaires
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26211:12"/>
of Gods Kingdome, and our owne ſaluation, and that the counſell of the Holy Ghoſt is; that<note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>if any ſpeake,</hi> hee ſhould <hi>ſpeake as the words of God,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note> that <hi>ſuch communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> ſhould <hi>proceed out of our mouthes, as is good for the vſe of edifying:</hi> giue me leaue therefore to propound a queſtion to you about theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conuert.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I like the motion paſſing well, and indeed there is too little of this good practiſe in theſe daies; chriſtian commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26211:12"/>
growes too much out of vſe, which ſhewes the want &amp; ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of grace; for there is the like correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between the heart and tongue, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the bell and clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: if the bell be ſtirred, the clapper cannot lye ſtill: and if the heart bee moued with delight in ſpirituall things, the tongue cannot chuſe but talke thereof: and where the tongue yeelds no other but an earthie ſound, there you may be ſure to finde no other but an earthly heart, no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26211:13"/>
pure good metall, no heauenly grace to bee found in the heart: Now therefore let mee heare the queſtion, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my poore mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge, I will bee ready to ſhape an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>Ought not euery one while he liues in this world, to know as a thing certaine, whether hee ſhall be ſaued, and ſo be tranſlated out of this earthly tabernacle, into the heauenly paradice, whenſoeuer hee ſhall be called away by death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conuert.</speaker>
               <p>Yes vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26211:13"/>
which I prooue thus,<note n="c" place="margin">Mar. 16.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that beleeueth</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>ſhall bee ſaued, but he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not, ſhall bee damned:</hi> This muſt euery one know as an vndoubted truth; and withall he is bound to know whether hee beleeueth, according to that charge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle:<note n="d" place="margin">2 Corin. 13.5:</note> 
                  <hi>Examine your ſelues whether you bee in the Faith: know you not that Chriſt is in you, except you bee reprobates?</hi> Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it will follow, that euery one muſt know whether hee ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and therefore ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26211:14"/>
as put their ſoules to a venture, cannot be ſaued, for as much as they take not the right courſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God thereto; namely, to prooue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the faith, and Chriſt in them. And further, whom the Lord intendeth to beſtow hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon, hee ſets his<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeale</hi> and marke vpon them, whereby he claims them for his owne, and he beſtowes loue-tokens on them, which are the ſauing graces of his holy ſpirit, whereof he is very charie, ſetting great ſtore by them, ſo that hee will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26211:14"/>
not beſtow them on caſt-awaies, but onely on his dearely beloued ones; which markes and loue-tokens, as they are very precious, ſo as many as receiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though they doubt) they need not doubt but that they ſhall bee ſaued, for God is not <hi>variable</hi> in his loue: but he that hath not theſe ſignes in him, whereby he may know that he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſhall (if he die in that comfortles ſtate) be ſure to haue his portion with deuills,<note n="g" place="margin">Reu. 21.8.</note> 
                  <hi>in the burning lake,</hi> for euer after death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>If the caſe ſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26211:15"/>
ſo, I thinke it lies euery one vpon, not to dallie with their owne ſoules, as men doe now adaies, but to deale ſoundly, and conſider ſincerely with themſelus, whether they haue receiued theſe gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den markes, and loue-to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of God, or whether they ſtill retaine the blacke brand of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill which they were borne with, the which ſo long as they retaine on them, the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ownes them; but if they can get it<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>waſhed</hi> out by the bloud of Chriſt, and Gods marks
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26211:15"/>
ſet vpon them, then hath the Deuill no more right or claime vnto them; for the Lord from that time forward, euen for euer, doth take them for his owne peculiar ones: But what ſay you now of thoſe that mourne after God, in the anguiſh of their ſoules, longing for the aſſurance of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and labouring to get this knowledge of their ſaluation, but yet cannot finde it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>This I ſay, or rather Chriſt himſelfe,<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 5.4</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that</hi> (ſo)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26211:16"/>
                  <hi>mourne, for they ſhall bee comforted;</hi> and though they now ſorrow, yet their<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>ſorrow ſhall bee turned into ioy:</hi> nay, great cauſe of reioycing haue they, that they can thus mourne: neyther is it poſſible for ſuch to bee without ſome ſure ſignes wherby they may know that they ſhall be ſaued; for euen this their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice (they being thus<note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſicke of loue</hi>) longing and labouring after Chriſt, is a ſure ſigne to them, though they ſhould haue no other: but indeed this cannot goe alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26211:16"/>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How comes it then to paſſe, that they take no notice hereof in themſelues, but rather feare that they ſhall not be ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe they are eyther new-borne babes in Chriſt, and therefore being as infants though they bee aliue, yet haue not as yet vnderſtanding to know that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others of riper age diſcerne in them, and they alſo by experience and growth in grace ſhal afterwards perceiue in themſelues; or elſe they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26211:17"/>
are diſtempered with ſome ſtrong fit of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby they are ſo aſtonied and benummed, that they haue not<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 77.7 8.</note> a feeling of that which otherwiſe they might perceiue in their ſoules: like as one halfe frozen, &amp; almoſt ſtiffe with cold, feeles no warmth at all in himſelfe, and yet there is ſome in him; for elſe there could be no life or breath remaining in him: Or laſtly, ſuch they are as haue taken a ſurfet of ſinne, wherby they haue beene ouercome; thus while they are ſoul-ſick,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26211:17"/>
their ſpirituall ſenſes are corrupted, ſo as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 88.14.</note> ſee the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome countenance of Gods fauour ſhining on them ſo clearely, nor<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 51.8.12.</note> heare the Lord ſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto them, nor taſte how good the Lord is to their ſoules in ſpeciall, nor reliſh religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes ſo ſauourlie, nor feele heauenly comforts ſo ſenſibly, as otherwiſe they might. And yet this ſurfet they ſhall out-grow in time, by vſing themſelues to a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of Chriſtian practiſe, and by the helpe of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26211:18"/>
Phyſicke of Gods word rightly applied, which holpe the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the like caſe, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered, <hi>Pſal</hi> 73.17. neither is it maruell though ſuch doe iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe of themſelues, for the preſent; ſeeing wee know that ſicke folkes are not competent or meet iudges of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: for they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times feele nothing but paine or ſickneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as others know, that there is in them more health then ſickneſſe, or at leaſt ſome health.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Now then to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26211:18"/>
come to your ſelfe (for it is the part of euery wiſe man, to be beſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his own eſtate.) Let mee a little examine your Euidences: haue you ſome good aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that you ſhall bee ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I praiſe God, elſe how could I haue any comfort? elſe my very meat ſhould be turned into gall, &amp; teares ſhould bee my drinke; well might my eyes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe all reſt, and my ſoule all comfort, knowing none other, but that I ſhould<note n="p" place="margin">Iob. 18.14.</note> 
                  <hi>goe to the king of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26211:19"/>
feare, into a Land darke as darkneſse it ſelfe:</hi> And ſure I am, that the<note n="q" place="margin">Mark. 8 36.</note> whole World, with the<note n="r" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.11.</note> beſt of all earthly things, cannot affoord true, ſound, and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall comfort, to the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting of the conſcience, &amp; reioycing of the heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How doe you know that you ſhall bee ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, by that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-grace, from whence all other ſauing graces flow, namely true iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith, a ſparke of this pious faith, I find is kindled in me, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26211:19"/>
this I build; GOD hath promiſed,<note place="margin">The firſt ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Iohn 3.36.</note> that <hi>hee which beleeueth ſhall be ſaued:</hi> Now then ſeeing I belieue (that is, am tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded that Chriſt is my Sauiour, that hee died for my ſinnes, and fulfilled the Law, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure mee perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes) therefore I know I ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It is nothing to ſay you beleeue, but let mee heare if you can proue it? how know you that yours is true faith, and not meere mocke-faith, which is ſo rife in the world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:26211:20"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe it hath beene rightly bred and begotten in me, and that by the ſpirituall ſeede of Gods word, according to that ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle;<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God:</hi> Thus then I came by Faith; firſt by hearing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Law prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, I ſaw my ſelfe to be in a damnable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature, a wretched ſinner, yea wholly ſinful, and therefore accurſed, by the iuſt ſentence of Gods moſt righteous Law, deſeruing nothing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26211:20"/>
but the horrible wrath of God, and lying open to the vengeance of eternal fire, ſo that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing betweene me and hell, but onely a poore, ſimple, craſie, tottering life, which I knew not how ſoone or ſuddenly it might be ſurpriſed by death; the conſideration whereof, wrought in mee terror of conſcience, dread of hell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, deſpairing of any hope or helpe in my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>And what then, did you reſt quiet in the ſight of this your wofull miſerie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:26211:21"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Oh it was not poſſible my poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule ſhould find any reſt in this eſtate, nay if I had heard no better ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, I ſhould haue bin ſwallowed vp of deſpair: but then in the next place I came<note n="*" place="margin">This is the cape of good hope in ſayling to heauen.</note> to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that God hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed and ſent his own ſonne to<note n="t" place="margin">Iſa. 61.1. Luk. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>preach good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings vnto the poore, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of ſight to the blind, to binde vp the broken hearted, and ſet at liberty ſuch as are bruiſed:</hi> more plainly, I learned by the doctrine of the Goſpell, that God of his rich mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26211:21"/>
hath giuen his ſonne, Chriſt Ieſus, very God and man, to be a Sauiour vnto ſinfull men, euen to as many as beleeue in him, and hath<note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded mee out of the number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaued by him, but hath offered him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee amongſt others <hi>which are weary and heauy laden with their ſins,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto mee all:</hi> (euen all ſuch) and hath alſo<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 3.23.</note> commanded, yea euen<note n="y" place="margin">Cor. 5.20.</note> intreated mee, to beleiue in him: Thus my heart was drawne and wonne, to take him and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26211:22"/>
apply him a Sauiour to my owne ſoule, thinking my ſelfe bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inuitation of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God: and what a beaſt were I, if I ſhould not accept of ſo free a profer of his Sonne, as he hath made vnto me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Thus you haue ſhewed mee well how you came by faith, and I ſee you haue come ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly by it; whereby it appeares that it is not like <hi>Iacobs</hi> veniſon too quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie found to bee of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26211:22"/>
right kinde, nor like <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs</hi> gourd, too ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſprung to continue long, but like the<note n="z" place="margin">2 Sam. 23.15, 16.</note> water of Bethlehem, much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for, &amp; hardly obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; now ſhew mee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how you vſe it: ſince you got it, what fruites doth it bring forth, whereby you may know more eaſily whether it be true, and<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>As fire may bee diſcerned by heat,<note place="margin">6 Notes of true faith.</note> and life by motion, ſo may my faith by the fruites thereof: For firſt, it ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth me to<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>quench the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26211:23"/>
fierie darts of that euil one,</hi> to reſiſt (not without ſome comfortable victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) the ſuggeſtions of Sathan wherwith he buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets me; and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, that ſame temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of doubting whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the promiſes of God belong to me or no: for that I am not ouercome of this doubting, and ſunke vnder it, but ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle and wreſtle with it, and with vnbeliefe, that is by the power of faith. Secondly, it makes mee earneſtly deſire to bee more and more reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to God, that is, more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26211:23"/>
fullie aſſured of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, that I am at peace with him, and hee well pleaſed with mee; to whom by nature I was an vtter enemy; it makes mee crie,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 106.4</note> 
                  <hi>remember mee O Lord with the fauour of thy people,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 84.5.</note> 
                  <hi>releaſe thy anger toward mee turne thy fac vnto mee,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 31.16</note> 
                  <hi>cauſe thy face to ſhine vnto thy ſeruant, and ſaue mee through thy mercy.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, my faith makes mee labour to pleaſe God, though it bee with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing my ſelfe, and to doe the will of God, yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe things which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26211:24"/>
croſſe my owne will, as it cauſed <hi>Abraham</hi> to<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 22.10.</note> offer his dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Iſaac,</hi> though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would haue gone ful ſore againſt his heart; and heereby <hi>Enoch</hi> was<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 11.5</note> 
                  <hi>reported of, that had had pleaſed God.</hi> Fourthly, by it my heart is in ſome meaſure purified from noyſome luſts and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; as ſecret pride, ſelfe-loue, hypocriſie, carnal confidence, wrath malice, and the like, in that they are diſtaſtfull, yea loathſome to mee, ſo that <hi>the ſpirit</hi> within me <hi>fighteth againſt the fleſh,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:26211:24"/>
that is, grace reſiſteth and ſubdueth corruption. Fiftly, it makes me long after Chriſt, to taſt more fully of his ſweetneſſe and to bee<note n="h" place="margin">Can. 1.2</note> kiſſed <hi>with the kiſſes of his mouth,</hi> that is, to haue a greater meaſure of heauenly graces, and greater and more liuely tokens of his loue, communicated to mee, whom and whoſe loue I do preferre aboue the whole world, euen in my hart. Laſtly, my faith brings forth in mee the ſweet fruit of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirituall ioy; for,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> beleeuing in him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26211:25"/>
                  <hi>whome wee haue not ſeene</hi> (that is Chriſt the Lord) <hi>wee reioyce with ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, and ful of glory;</hi> which is therefore called the ioy<note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 1.25.</note> of faith, becauſe it proceeds from thence: Thus my faith is<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> a working faith, and by theſe fruits and the like, I know it is not a vaine fancy, and vngrounded imagination, but a ſound and well-grounded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, whereby I am ingraffed into Chriſt: for to beleeue, is<note n="*" place="margin">Extra nos ire, &amp; in Chriſtum tranſire.</note> to go out of our ſelues, and to goe into Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>If theſe things
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26211:25"/>
bee ſo, I am not able to obiect any thing againſt your faith, nay, all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels of hell ſhall neuer be able to ouerthrow it: But by what other ſigne doe you know that you ſhall be ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Well may my conuerſion plead ſenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the ſecond place, it being of the ſame age with faith: for there is no ſooner true faith wrought in the heart, but inſtantly there is a new Conuert made, and a ſinner <hi>become the ſonne of Abraham,</hi> and well may there then be <hi>ioy in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26211:26"/>
heauen for a ſinner that is conuerted.</hi> So then there is an effectual calling and conuerſion wrought in mee; for the Lord of his vnſpeakeable goodneſſe hath <hi>deliuered mee out of the power of darkneſſe, and tranſlated mee into the kingdom of his deare ſon,</hi> that is, hee hath brought mee out of the miſerable eſtate of nature wherein I was borne, into the happy eſtate of grace, wherein I now ſtand:<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Rom. 8.30.</note> this calling is a ſure ſigne that one is ordained to euerlaſting life; for, <hi>whom the Lord hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26211:26"/>
thoſe hee hath alſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified:</hi> therefore heereby I am comfortably aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of my ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Our Sauiour tels vs,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 22.14.</note> that there are <hi>many called, but few choſen:</hi> how then can this bee a ſigne vnto you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>There is a two-fold calling of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: an outward, and an inward; the Lord calls outwardly all thoſe to whom the Goſpell is preached; for ſuch he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to come to him by beleeuing and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that they might be ſaued, but many ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26211:27"/>
thus to come vnto him, and therefore are not effectually called: like as if you ſhould call a man that is in a dead ſleep, who hears you not, &amp; therefore lies ſnorting ſtill; it may be truly ſaid, he was not called vp, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee did not awaken and come vnto you: ſo the outward calling by the voyce of the Goſpel alone, is not ſufficient to ſaluation, therefore the Lord calls his elect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly alſo by his ſpirit, and this is that whereof I ſpeake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>But how know
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26211:27"/>
you that you are thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly &amp; effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and conuerted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">2 Notes of effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al calling.</note> By the eccho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe, and ſecret an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of my heart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the voyce and call of God; for the Lord ſaith,<note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 27.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke</hi> thou <hi>my face, my heart anſwereth, thy face, O Lord, will I ſeeke:</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto mee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all yee that are weary and heauy loden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> and<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 8.37</note> 
                  <hi>if any man thirſt, let him come vnto mee and drinke;</hi> my heart anſwereth; O Lord, it is the deſire of my ſoule to come vnto thee, oh that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26211:28"/>
I could come, oh how ſhall I come, helpe mee that I may come, <hi>draw mee and I will runne after thee;</hi> ſeeing my hart doth thus inwardly anſwere his call, it is a certaine ſigne that I heare him call: which I could not vnleſſe hee did call, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and effectually.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Lord hath wrought in mee a wonderfull and ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall change, ſo that I am contrary to that I was by nature (<note n="*" place="margin">Non noua ſubſtantia creatura, ſed labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facta repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur.</note> as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the quality and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of my ſoule) now louing that good
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26211:28"/>
which then I hated, and hating now that euill which before I loued; therefore I am a new creature, and liue a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, yea Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in mee: for by the power of the ſpirit flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into mee from Chriſt my head, I liue vnto God, not vnto my ſelfe; and I would not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the condition wherein I was before, for all the worlds good, but tremble to thinke vpon it, accounting it as the ſuburbs and mouth of hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I doe verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26211:29"/>
you, for they which haue thus ſeen and taſted of hell in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, will take heed how they come neere it again ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they liue: herein is that verified, the burnt childe dreads the fire. But name vnto mee a third ſigne of your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes I ſee Iuſtification offering it ſelfe, and comming forth hand in hand with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, as beeing the daughters of one mother Faith, &amp; two ſiſters born at one birth, hand-faſted by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:26211:29"/>
8.30. neuer to bee ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:<note place="margin">The third ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Rom. 8.30.</note> ſo then I am iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that is, I am accepted of God perfectly righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous through Chriſt, this ſigne neuer failes, for <hi>whom</hi> God <hi>iuſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How can you proue, that you are thus iuſtified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is the daughter of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parent, Faith, which faith beeing in mee, I am thereby onely iuſtified,<note n="*" place="margin">Iuſtification is the daughter of the true mother Faith, not of works, the falſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for ſhee ſaith, let it be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt &amp; our ſelues.</note> and not by workes, (vnleſſe it bee to declare me iuſt before men) for I cannot bee ſo popiſhly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26211:30"/>
fond as to thinke that men muſt licke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues whole with their owne righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſts in two things; the remiſſion of our ſins for Chriſts paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, and the imputation of his perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to vs, I haue ſome proofe of both: for firſt I know that God doth pardon and forgiue mee all my ſinnes, for I doe heartily confeſſe them to him, with a deteſtation of them: and <hi>if we confeſse our ſinnes, hee is faithfull, and iuſt to forgiue vs our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26211:30"/>
ſinnes,</hi> as<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 1.9.</note> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Secondly, I know that God doth reckon Chriſts righteouſnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, as verily as if I had perſonally perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it my ſelfe, this I know by my peace of conſcience; for they which are thus<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>iuſtified by faith, haue peace toward God,</hi> and they only: thus am I one of thoſe<note n="f" place="margin">Reu. 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>that haue waſhed their long robes, and made them white in the bloud of the Lambe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede if the conſcience be truely pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, it is euident that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26211:31"/>
you are partaker of Chriſts perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: for what elſe can giue the Conſcience true peace; and not the drunken peace of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it hath followed grieuous trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnquietneſſe in my conſcience, as a calm followes after a ſtorme: for ſuch as neuer were afflicted in minde, and diſtreſſed in conſcience, neuer had true peace. 2 My peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">3 Notes of true peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> makes mee carefull to keepe a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (as it made the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26211:31"/>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Hebr. 13.18.</note> 
                  <hi>deſiring to liue honeſtly, and to haue</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>my conuerſation in godly pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> 3. This true peace makes my Conſcience not afraid to view it ſelf: whereas the euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is like the Elephant, which being guilty of his deformity, cannot abide to looke on his owne face in the water, but ſeekes muddy chanells, and fowle puddles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Let mee heare you name ſome other ſigne, from whence you gather aſſurance of your ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Mine Adoption
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26211:32"/>
is a ſign hereof: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I was by nature a baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of Satan; &amp; no child ſo like his father as I was like him, the Lord of his free grace &amp; fauour hath adopted me his childe, to traine mee vp vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, that I may inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with his own Son Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; by meanes whereof I haue right alſo<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.22.23.</note> to the creatures heere in this world, as being my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers goods; and the miſeries of this life<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mercies to me, and the glorious<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 1.14</note> Angells, become attenders on mee: O high fauours, O
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26211:32"/>
rich mercy, O inſtimable dignity, to bee the childe of God! Thus I truſt I am one of the number of Gods children.<note place="margin">The fourth ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Rom. 8.17.</note> Now none of them can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be depriued of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting inheritance, <hi>for if we be children, then are wee alſo heyres of God, &amp; ioyntheyrs with Chriſt.</hi> Seeing then I am one of them, I know I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit together with them yea with Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It is a common thing with men, yea with lewd and graceleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to ſay they are the children of God, as the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26211:33"/>
wicked Iewes,<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 8.41 44.</note> ſaid to our Sauiour, but hee tels them, they ar of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Deuill: how know you then that you are a true childe of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe I am regenerate; that is, borne againe;<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.13 5 Notes of a true child of God.</note> 
                  <hi>not of bloud,</hi> as by a ſecond naturall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, <hi>nor of the will of the fleſh,</hi> as by any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtrength or actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>nor of the will of man,</hi> as by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans endeuour or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, <hi>but of God, born of the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note> as water through ſpirituall<note n="c" place="margin">Tit 3.5</note> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ablution, being <hi>begotten by the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26211:33"/>
ſeed of his word:</hi> they which are thus begotten and borne of God, muſt needs be his children: &amp; that I am thus borne of the ſpirit, and ſo become a new creature, I haue ſhewed before, in that I am conuerted. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, looke what naturall affections are in a childe toward his father, ſuch ſpirituall affections are in mee towards God: if he frowne, I mourne; if he threaten, I tremble; if he ſmite, I ſtoop; if he ſmile, I am right glad; if hee ſpeake comfortablie, I reioyce hartily: I delight
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26211:34"/>
in nothing ſo much as the fauour of God, feare nothing ſo much as the loſſe of it: hauing found it, oh how faine would I keepe it: hauing loſt it, I cannot be at quiet till I recouer it: I can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to want all things ſo I haue it, and can finde contentment in nothing if I want it, my heauenly fathers fauour is more to mee then all the world. Thirdly, I know my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, by the ſpirit of adoption which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mee, and caſts out of me daily more and more the<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> ſpirit of bondage, a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26211:34"/>
terrifying &amp; tormenting conſcience: and it makes me with ſome comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confidence, and a true heart, vnfainedly to call vpon God, and to cal him my Father without either flattery or diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Fourthly,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> 
                  <hi>As many as are led by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, they are the ſons of God:</hi> by his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit am I led, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie doe I ſubmit my ſelfe, and vnfainedly deſire to bee wholly gouerned thereby, I deſire not to follow the blinde guide, carnall reaſon, nor the deceitfull guide, my own
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26211:35"/>
corrupt heart, but <hi>I ſet the Lord alwaies before mee,</hi> as a guide to direct mee in all things by that rule, whereby <hi>hee leades into al truth,</hi> euen his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie word: it is my delight to ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 25.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Leade mee in thy truth O Lord, and teach mee, for thou art the God of my ſaluation.</hi> Fiftly, whereas all the children of God do reſemble him their father, (for howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man may haue a childe nothing like him, yet God hath neuer a childe, but is in ſome meaſure like him) hereby
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26211:35"/>
I alſo know that I am his childe, becauſe I doe in ſome ſort reſemble him my heauenly Father. As hee is<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> holy<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 6.36.</note> mercifull, good,<note n="i" place="margin">Ma. 5.48</note> perfect; ſo doe I endeuour to conforme vnto him, hauing his bleſſed image imprinted in mee, and being renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto that<note n="k" place="margin">Ge. 1.26</note> likeneſſe, wherein the Lord crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; abhorring to bee of the number of them, who though they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues to bee Gods children, yet are as <hi>Nabal,</hi> ſo prophane and <hi>wicked, that a man cannot
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26211:36"/>
ſpeake vnto them;</hi> and ſurely, blaſphemie it were to thinke that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny likeneſſe betweene God and them, he ſuch a pure ſpirit, and they ſuch impure ſwine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Proceed vnto ſome other ſigne of your ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord will beſtow an euerlaſting <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance vpon all them that are ſanctified;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fift ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Act. 20.32.</note> ſuch a one am I, the Lord hath ſanctified mee by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, that is, hath made mee holy, whereas I was before, moſt vile, filthy, &amp; vnclean, wholly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26211:36"/>
ſinfull: Neither yet am I now quite and cleane freed from all ſinne, or perfectly holy; for alas,<note n="l" place="margin">Ro. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſee another law in my members rebelling againſt the law of my minde, and bringing me into captiuity of the law of ſinne:</hi> but I am freed from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and dominion of ſinne. And looke as in the twi-light or day-breake, ſome little glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering light there is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ſprea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the skie, yet mixed with much darkneſſe: euen ſo there is in mee the admixture of ſinne, and much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26211:37"/>
accompanying the light of ſanctifying grace, in euery part of me; yet this is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>That the day-ſtarre is riſen, and the morning-light now ſhineth in mee;</hi> and as for high-noone, perfection of holineſſe, I wait for it, and looke to enioy it in the higheſt heauen: for the<note n="m" place="margin">Pr. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>path of the iuſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more &amp; more vnto the perfect day.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>There are not a few, who though they can talke of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> notwithſtanding very prophane, yea lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26211:37"/>
perſons, hauing the vncleane iſſues of ſin, like plague-ſores running on them, going vp and downe with the leapers, crie in their mouth<note n="n" place="margin">Leui. 13.45.</note> 
                  <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleane, vncleane,</hi> therefore how know you that you are truely ſanctified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>If I could not ſhew a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween my ſelfe and ſuch vncleane beaſts,<note place="margin">Proofe of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the parts thereof.</note> I ſhould bee ſorry: thus then I prooue the Truth of my ſanctification: whereas it conſiſts in two things, namely, mortification &amp; quickening, I haue ſome proofe of both; for the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26211:38"/>
firſt,<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> I <hi>mortifie the deeds of the fleſh by the ſpirit:</hi> wherein I imitate the skilfull Chirurgion,<note place="margin">Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> who being to cut off ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureable member, firſt mortifieth it, that ſo it beeing made inſenſible, may be cut off more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, and with leſſe paine to the patient. And this courſe I take in mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſinnes: Firſt, I labour by ſearching to finde them out: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to finde my ſelfe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, and willing to be rid of them, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what infinite hurt they doe mee. Thirdly,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26211:38"/>
I fetch power from the death of Chriſt, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that he died to<note n="p" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.5.8.</note> kill ſinne in all that are his, and therefore that it is impoſſible for them to liue vnto ſinne, or ſinne to rule in them. 4.<note n="*" place="margin">The death of Chriſt as a ſalue applied to the ſore by faith, leaueth a print like it ſelfe in the ſoul, a ſpirituall death, or dying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne.</note> I apply this power of Chriſts death, as a ſtrong corraſiue, to this proud fleſh of mine, to the wounding and killing of the ſinne that is in mee: and thus I apply it; 1. Seeing that my ſinnes put Chriſt to death, I am reſolued, as the auenger of bloud, to follow the law vpon them, to get a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26211:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> a Writ for them, to doe by them, as they did by him, euen to purſue them vnto death, which put my elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Sauiour vnto death. Secondly, ſeeing I beleeue, that Chriſt died for mee, to kill ſinne in me, I ſee I neither muſt nor can<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 6.2.6.</note> ſuffer ſinne to liue, and raigne in me; for fhat were to make the death of Chriſt of none effect, vnto mee: Thus then though ſinne bee in mee, yet it hath receiued the deadly wound, by the death of Chriſt, neuer after to recouer againe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26211:39"/>
but lyes as<note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> thruſt thorow with his ſpeare; though life bee ſtill abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it, it is gaſping, and ſtrugling, languiſhing and dying, and ſhall at laſt bee vtterly extinct in death.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ro. 7.25.</note> I thanke God therefore through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>You haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to ſome good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: of mortification: but what ſay you now of quickning, which is the ſecond part of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>They which haue the one,<note place="margin">Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> can not want the other; therefore I finde
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26211:40"/>
alſo a quickning power of grace in mee, whereby I riſe vp out of the graue of ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſneſſe, and that after this manner; 1 I. la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by inquiring to find out that righteouſneſſe, which God requireth of mee. 2. I ſtriue for a willingneſſe of minde &amp; heart, to ſet thereupon, with all delight: which that I may do, 3. I fetch power from Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, conſidering, and beleeuing, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viued and roſe againe, for this very end, namely to procure, and giue to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26211:40"/>
all that are his, ſtrength and power, to<note n="t" place="margin">Rom 6.4.</note> liue vnto righteouſnes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it is as impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any ſuch to want this power, as for Chriſt to die in vaine. 4. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this power to my ſelfe, whereby the breath of ſpirituall life comes into my ſoule, and that after this maner:<note n="*" place="margin">To belieu that Chriſt roſe for mee, is to apply his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as a ſoueraign plaiſter to my heart: which is of ſuch a vertue that it muſt needs worke in me his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Seeing I beleeue that Chriſt roſe for mee, as verily as he is my Sauiour, ſo verily, muſt I, and ſhall I, ſhew forth this ſpirituall power in the practice of piety, and righteous liuing: Thus then there is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26211:41"/>
paſſion, and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rction in mee (as there is in euery true beleeuer) anſwerable to to the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reſurrection of Chriſt; as he died for ſin; and roſe againe for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſo I die to ſinne, and riſe againe to righteouſnes, in all the powers of my ſoule, and parts of my body, theſe being made the<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of thoſe, <hi>in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe vnto God.</hi> And this briefly is that ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication which I finde in me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>And ſurely this is that, which whoſoeuer
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26211:41"/>
finde in them, they are no leſſe than canonized in the Court of Heauen for Saints, and irreuocably regiſtred in Gods Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar of Saints. But what will you name in the next place, for a ſigne of your ſaluation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Repentance: which howſoeuer it doth not<note n="*" place="margin">Non re ſed ratione Polanus</note> really differ from Sanctification, yet in ſome reſpect (as<note n="“" place="margin">Perkins.</note> ſome haue well obſerued) it doth, as being ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thereto, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there-from as the fruit thereof: for where the Lord infuſeth ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26211:42"/>
grace into the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, will, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Conuert; then according vnto this grace receiued, he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in turning to the Lord: and though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance bee diſcerned, before eyther Faith, or Sanctification; yet that hinders not, but that they are before it in<note n="*" place="margin">Ordinae natura.</note> order of nature; like as in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the light, and ſunne-beames, are ſeene before the bodie of the Sunne, and yet in order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is before them, and they proceed from it. But to come neerer
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26211:42"/>
the matter, I repent me of my ſinnes; for I turne from all ſinne to God, in heart, and deſire, and labour to expreſſe the ſame,<note place="margin">The ſixt ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Eze. 18.21.</note> by a carefull fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of my life, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euill, and doing good, hauing reſpect vnto all Gods commandements. Now God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that hee which thus <hi>turneth from all his ſins, ſhall ſurely liue</hi> for euer, <hi>and ſhall not dye</hi> eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; therefore hereby I know I ſhall bee ſaued: for this is a ſalue for all ſores, and a preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26211:43"/>
to cure all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall diſeaſes of the ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>All the doubt will be whether you doe truely repent, how can you make that appeare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5 Notes, of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note>Thus: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I grieue in my heart for my ſinnes, chiefly, in regard that thereby I offend my good<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 51.4</note> God, who alwaies hath been, and is abundantly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious vnto mee: this pierceth my ſoule, that I ſhould bee ſo vndutifull toward him. Secondly, I<note n="x" place="margin">Pſa. 119.104.</note> hate, loath, and deteſt in ſome meaſure, all ſin
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26211:43"/>
in my heart, bearing my ſelfe toward it as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; and when I haue beene ouercome by the deceit thereof, I loue it not the better, but hate it much the more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when I haue reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered my ſelfe againe: I deale with my ſinne, as <hi>Amnon</hi> dealt with his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Thamer:</hi> who when he had ſatisfied his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed luſt, did hate her more than euer hee had loued her before, and thruſt hir out of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and preſence, as not abiding the ſight of her. Thirdly,<note n="y" place="margin">Pſa. 119.57.</note> I reſolue
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26211:44"/>
in truth, with a conſtant purpoſe, and ſettled de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, not to doe any thing that I know to bee ſinne, and ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Lord; the Lord hee knowes, that I do not purpoſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my ſelfe in any knowne ſin whatſoeuer. Fourthly, I ſtriue, &amp;<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 119.101.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deuour in the whole courſe of my life, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake euery knowne ſinne, and to come to the fight of vnknowne ſins which as yet I haue not taken notice of, that I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them alſo. I doe as heartily deſire, to forgoe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26211:44"/>
my ſins, as to haue them forgiuen; to part with them, as to haue them pardoned: whereas the man vnregenerate, will at no hand part with his ſinne:<note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 20.1.2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>for it is ſweet in his mouth, hee hides it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his tongue, hee ſpares it, and forſakes it not, but keepes it ſtill within his mouth,</hi> (as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſpeaks) he will as ſoon part with a limme, nay his life, as with his ſweet ſinne: But for my part, I deſire that the bloud of Chriſt may as well waſh away the filthineſſe of my ſinne, as the guiltineſſe thereof.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26211:45"/>
5. I bring forth the right and kindly fruit of true repentance, namely, new obedience, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly grow out of any other roote than this: thus it is my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall care to<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 1.6.</note> walke in all the commandements, and ordinances of the Lord without reproofe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Bet is not all this that you doe, for feare of hell, and condemnation onely?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely, but partly for loue I beare to God; and partly for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred I beare to ſinne: for though I knew there
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26211:45"/>
were no day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when men ſhall giue an account of all their doings, and receiue a full reward according thereunto; or though I could bee aſſured that there were no hell to take vengeance on wicked doers, yet would I neuer commit thoſe foule and filthy ſinnes which I ſee ſome commit continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to my griefe: though they are well-pleaſing to ſinfull corrupt nature, and ſo were to mee, whiles I was carnall, now I doe abhor them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemes you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26211:46"/>
make true griefe for ſin a ſigne of true repentance: ſhew mee then how god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow, which is only in the faithfull, may bee knowne from <hi>worldly ſorrow,</hi> which <hi>cauſeth death,</hi> and was in <hi>Cain, Saul, Ahab, Herod, Iudas</hi> and may bee in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Difference betweene worldly and godly ſorrow.</note>Hee that hath godly ſorrow is at leaſt perſwaded, that his ſins are pardonable, not that they are<note n="c" place="margin">Ge. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>greater than may bee forgiuen,</hi> as <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid; but that they may bee pardoned by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely farre-ſurpaſſing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26211:46"/>
mercy of God. 2. Hee loues the Preacher, and other wel-diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that tell him of his faults, and ſhew him his ſins; though happily reprouing him ſharpely for them: and hee reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceth and regardeth Gods word the more, that he ſees his ſinne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby: the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was in <hi>Ahab,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1 Kings 22.8.</note> who hated the Prophet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee dealt plainely with him; and <hi>Herod</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 14.3.4.</note> who depriued <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, both of liberty and life, becauſe he tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26211:47"/>
his copy-hold, in reprouing his inceſtuous life. 3. Godly ſorrow driues a man neerer to God by prayer, and makes him ſeeke to the Miniſter, &amp; to the godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for counſell; to the word, &amp; ſpirituall means for comfort: but the ſorrow of the world driues a man further from God &amp; the means; as in <hi>Saul,</hi> who went to a witch, and <hi>Iudas</hi> who hanged himſelfe, both of them haſting to get as far from God, as the moſt remote place in all the world, euen hell it ſelfe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26211:47"/>
could make them. 4. The ſorrow of him that is truely-penitent, is moſt occupied about the<note n="*" place="margin">Malum culpae.</note> euil of ſinne; the ſorrow of others, moſt about the<note n="“" place="margin">Malum poena.</note> euill of puniſhment, all their care, and thoughts are taken vp therewith: and were it not for that, the euill of their ſinne, ſhould not trouble their minds, or diſquiet them one whit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>You named new obedience, for a note of true repentance, &amp; that not amiſſe if it bee true, vnfained, and of the right kinde. But how
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26211:48"/>
proue you this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 Notes of true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note>Firſt, becauſe it is obedience of the whole man, inward, as well as outward: for a true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dienciarie vnto God, muſt be both ſound, and ſtreight, ſound in heart, &amp; ſtreight in life, all ouer obedient; though hee bee not perfect. 2. It is obedience, yeelded to the whole law of God, to precept as well as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and to one precept as well as to an other: whereas they which are falſe hearted in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, are alſo lame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and will be diſpenſed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26211:48"/>
withall in ſome things, they can be content that ſome of their ſins ſhould dye, with the leane cattel ſlaine by<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul;</hi> but they haue ſome one or two, or more fat ſinnes, which they will needs haue ſpared. I praiſe God (in humility I ſpeak it) I haue no ſuch reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in my obedience; but that my maſter-ſins, &amp; darling-ſins, ſhould be put to the ſword, as well as others of inferiour ranke. 3. It is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the whole courſe of my life; it doth not take me now and then at
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26211:49"/>
times, like the Fit of an Ague, but is conſtant, and continuall. For a man may croſſe the way to heauen often-times, in, and out, and yet neuer come thither; but he that holds on conſtantly in the way, ſhall bee ſure of heauen. Thus true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is Catholike, that is, vniuerſall: and they, &amp; none but they, deſerue the name of good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks indeed, which are carefull to yeeld to God this true, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall (though imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) obedience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:26211:49"/>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Hitherto you haue mentioned ſuch graces as are more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and concerne the whole perſon renewed: now if you thinke good alledge ſome ſpeciall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which make their abode in ſeuerall ſeats of the ſoule: and firſt for knowledge, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideth in the minde, is not this a ſigne of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which you diſcerne in your ſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Sauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is indeed a true ſigne, which is called<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>the vnction of the holy one,</hi> and Chriſts<note n="h" place="margin">Reu. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>eye-ſalue;</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:26211:50"/>
becauſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, being as it were anointed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, is inlightned to ſee, and diſcerne thoſe things, which before it neither did, nor could; it comprehendeth<note n="i" place="margin">Col. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vnderſtanding,</hi> (that is a right conceiuing of the truth of God) <hi>and wiſedome,</hi> (that is, a right applying thereof, wiſely and diſcreetly, to all our particular actions, for the right ordering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:<note place="margin">The ſeuenth ſigne of ſaluation taken our of Joh. 17.3.</note>) this knowledge of <hi>God, is life eternall;</hi> both becauſe it is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26211:50"/>
it is the meanes wherby we attain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: now then ſeeing I haue found this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I am ſure I cannot loſe eternall life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Euery one is a beaſt by his owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: he therefore that wants this knowledge of God, doth not much differ from a bruit beaſt: and<note n="*" place="margin">Praeſtat naſci iume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tum quam comparari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iumento.</note> better were it to be borne a beaſt, than being borne a man, to become thus like a beaſt. But how doe you proue that yours is this ſauing knowledge, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that common
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26211:51"/>
knowledge of Gods word &amp; religion, which may bee in the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5. Notes of true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge</note>This will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the better by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them together. Firſt then, the common knowledge which may bee found in reprobates is generall: they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſpirituall things in a generall confuſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; not vnlike the<note n="k" place="margin">Mar. 8.24.</note> blinde man cured by our Sauiour, who at the firſt opening of his eyes, ſaw men aloofe off, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as trees: they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide to bring it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26211:51"/>
home to themſelues; but I apply my knowledge to my ſelfe, deſiring to know chiefly, how things ſtand at home in my owne ſoule. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, their knowledge is partiall; they deſire not to bee acquainted with all the waies of God, but are, and will be wilfully ignorant of ſome things; they will not know that to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, which they like well of, nor that to bee good which they doe diſlike, though it be made plain and euident vnto them: but I deſire to know the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26211:52"/>
whole truth of God, yea that which is diſreliſhing at the firſt vnto mee. Thirdly, their knowledg puffs them vp with pride; thy be not a little proud thereof: but mine hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles mee; for the more light of knowledge ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in mee, the more I ſee the corruptions of my heart, and life there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; which miniſter grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matter daily of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation to me. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all that they know, or ſpeake, is onely from heare-ſay; for they haue no experience thereof in themſelues; they know,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26211:52"/>
and learne Gods truth by rote, but I learne it by heart; my knowledge is experimentall; I finde the truth thereof in my owne experience. Fiftly, their knowledge is not ioyned with conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practice; whereas that is but raw knowledge that is not well digeſted into practice: theſe two ſhould alwayes goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably together; for knowledge without pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is lame, and practice without knowledge is blinde. And if the lame and blind were hated of<note n="e" place="margin">2. Sa. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauids</hi> ſoule; much
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26211:53"/>
more are theſe hatefull to the ſoule of the Lord, as an abhominable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: but my knowledge is practicall, it walks vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the feet of practice, &amp; my practice ſees with the eyes of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: <hi>hereby wee know that wee know God, if wee keepe his commandements,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.3. Though, then, there be many which know Chriſt to profeſſe him, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall not be known of him (for hee will ſay vnto them in that day,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me, I know you not,</hi> becauſe they haue
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26211:53"/>
not the ſauing knowledge of him) yet I can thus bring proofe, that I rightly know him, or<note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> rather am knowne of him, wherby I alſo know that I ſhall hereafter liue, and raigne for euer with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Thus it appeares that the true knowledge of Chriſt doth counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize, yea and far excell all other knowledge whatſoeuer: for if one know Chriſt, it matters little though he be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of other things; but if hee bee ignorant of Chriſt, it matters nothing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26211:54"/>
though hee knowe all things: wherefore the wiſeſt wordly men, with all their knowledge, ſhall periſh for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. So that I can well aſſent vnto him, who ſaith, that the knowledge of God,<note place="margin">Greenham.</note> is as neceſſary an Art for Chriſtians, as the Art of husbandry is for husbandmen. Now, if you thinke good, name another ſpeciall grace, as the ſigne of your ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eight ſigne of ſaluation taken out of Rom. 8.24.</note>I haue a true hope of eternall life: which who ſo haue, they ſhall be ſaued; for <hi>wee
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26211:54"/>
are ſaued by hope,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle: this grace alſo the Lord of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath vouchſafed mee, to bee as <hi>an anker to my ſoule, both ſure, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt,</hi> to hold mee to the port, that I be not driuen backe with boyſterous ſtormes; and than beares vp my head aboue water, in the ſeas of dangers, in this preſent world, that I ſinke not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>But the hope of moſt men is a falſe hope, &amp; deſperate mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, (as if a man hauing his throat cut, or being thruſt through the heart,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26211:55"/>
ſhould yet hope to liue, euery body would bee ready to deride his idle fancy, or at leaſt to pitie his extreme follie) the hope of ſuch <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and be cut off, and their truſt ſhall bee as a ſpiders web:</hi> how know you then that yours is a true hope?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Truth it is, that the common hope of men is ſuch, that they doe rather dream than hope: and though they thinke they haue faſt hold of it in their hearts, yet it is but as a child that catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at the ſhadow on the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:26211:55"/>
wall, hee thinks he holds it faſt cloſed in his hand, but when he openeth his hand there is nothing in it; ſo when their hearts ſhall be laid open before God, the ſhaddowlike hope being vaniſhed, there ſhall be no ſuch thing found in their hearts, and they ſhall haue hope to ſeek, when it will bee too late to finde it.<note place="margin">4 Notes of true hope.</note> Firſt therefore I proue that my hope is true, from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wheron it is<note n="p" place="margin">Heb 11 1.</note> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that is Faith: for as it is impoſſible for a mighty Caſtle to hang in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26211:56"/>
the ayre, or to ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either ground or foundation, euen ſo, and much more impoſſible is it for hope to be, or abide without faith. Such therefore as boaſt of hope, and are barren of faith, may well be ſaid to dreame of building ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the ayre: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe beleeue, and therefore doe I hope, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the promiſes of God by faith; and ſo hoping and looking for the performance and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment thereof: which faith, the ground-worke, I haue formerly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26211:56"/>
proued to be effectually begun in mee. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, true hope followes an effectual calling: for firſt God calls men to ſaluation, and then hee giues them to hope for it; therefore the Apoſtle ſtiles it; <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 1.18</note> 
                  <hi>hope of his calling.</hi> Such therefore as hope for heauen, not being effectually called vnto it, come before they are called, and are like to ſpeed accordingly. It was<note n="r" place="margin">Eſter. 4.11.</note>death to ruſh into the preſence of <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> vncalled: and ſure, eternall death ſhall cut them off, ſhort, of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26211:57"/>
home, which think to ruſh rudely into the <hi>Holieſt of all,</hi> the inner Court of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, euen the higheſt heauen, being neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and truely called thither: but well may I hope, for I am truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as I haue alſo proued before. Thirdly, my hope makes me vſe dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently all good meanes appointed by God, for the obtaining of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for hee that hath good hope to obtaine his wiſhed deſire, will ſhew it by his induſtrious vſe of the beſt meanes, for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26211:57"/>
the compaſſing therof: ſo hee that in the mourning hopes to be 50. miles off by ſunne-ſet, will not fit him down, or lay himſelf to ſleep, but get on horſe-backe, and be riding on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on his way; and he that hopes to liue long, will not ſtarue himſelfe, but vſe the beſt diet for preſeruing his life, 4. It makes me fit my ſelfe by holineſſe, for that which I hope for, namely the full fruition of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ous preſence of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly-pure, and holy God in heauen, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:26211:58"/>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.3</note> 
                  <hi>Euery one that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelfe, euen as God is pure:</hi> not vnlike to one who hoping to get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe into the preſence of the King with his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, doth addreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in all ſutab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, both in apparell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, and ſpeech, for the preſence of his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It appeares your hope is found, and good, euen that<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>which maketh not aſhamed:</hi> and <hi>the God of hope fill you therewith,</hi> and <hi>grant that you may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound therein through the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:26211:58"/>
Holy Ghoſt.</hi> But by what other ſigne doe you know that you ſhall bee ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>I finde in my heart a true loue of God, now I haue learned out of the word, that <hi>the Lord hath promiſed the crowne of life to them that loue him,</hi> &amp;c. I make no queſtion but hee will bee as good as his word, who neuer failed therein, ſince the world began: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I know, that the crowne of life is mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>All ſay they loue God, and profeſſe great friendſhip to him:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:26211:59"/>
                  <hi>neuertheleſse</hi> moſt <hi>flatter him with their mouth, and lye vnto him with their tongues, for their heart is not right with him,</hi> How know you then that you loue him in truth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7. Notes of true loue of God.</note>Whereas there are three things in loue, affection to the thing beloued, a deſire of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction with it, and a well-pleaſing content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken in the enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, all theſe I find in ſome meaſure in mee, toward my God, ſo that I know I loue him truly, which I further proue by theſe notes: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:26211:59"/>
I prize and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate him aboue all worldly things; yea, mine owne life: ſo that I can truely ſay with that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyr <hi>Ignatius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> I eſteeme no viſible thing, nor yet inuiſible, ſo that I may haue Chriſt:<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 3.8</note> 
                  <hi>yea, doubtleſse I count all things but loſse</hi> in compariſon of him, and <hi>do count them but dung, that I may winne him.</hi> Neither is this a mercenarie loue, hired with the wages of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: for, though there were no heauen, O Lord, I would loue thee: but ſeeing there is a heauen,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:26211:60"/>
I will account of it, and labour to obtaine it; yet ſtill will I loue thee for thy goodneſſe ſake, O Lord: for thou thy ſelfe art reward enough, though there were no more. Secondly, I am carefull, and vnfainedly deſirous, to pleaſe the Lord in all things; euen as we ſee, that men are loth to croſſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe thoſe whom they entirely loue and affect. Heerupon I giue my ſelfe to loue that which hee loueth, and to hate that which he hateth.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 45.7</note> 
                  <hi>He lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth righteouſnes, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:26211:60"/>
wickednes:</hi> and ſo doe I, though not in equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (for that is impoſſible) yet in ſimilitude, and conformity: for it is required and expected, (as the Prophet ſaith)<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They that loue the Lord, hate euill:</hi> thus I ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour my ſelfe,<note n="y" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>as God is, euen ſo to bee in this worldr</hi> Thirdly, a man may knowe his loue to any thing, by the zeale and heat of affection, whereby he is carried to that thing which hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Thus euery man is tranſported, and as it were eaten vp with one
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:26211:61"/>
zeale, or other; ſome with the zeale of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as <hi>Eſau</hi> was, who for a meſſe of pottage ſould his birth-right; ſome with the zeale of honour, as <hi>Abſalom</hi> was, who, for to gette a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſought to draw bloud of his owne father; ſome with the zeale of money, as <hi>Iudas</hi> was, who for his thirty peeces ſold his Lord &amp; Sauiour. By my zeale I know my loue to God: for, tho I bee not eaten vp with zeale as<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 69 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was (oh I would I were ſo too) yet I feele it burning
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:26211:61"/>
within mee, as<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 20.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremiah</hi> did: <hi>my heart is hot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, and the fire kindled:</hi> my zeale carrieth mee to God. Fourthly, I loue his<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ. 119.97.</hi> Qui diligit legem, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git regem.</note> word, and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, prayer, and all other holy exerciſes: whereby as I haue graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intercourſe, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly conference, with the bleſſed Trinity; ſo in eſpeciall with Chriſt my wel-beloued, who therin cauſeth mee to heare his ſweet voyce, and to ſee his louely countenance: for which cauſe I alſo loue the houſe of God, ſo that I can no leſſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:26211:62"/>
heartily, than merrily, ſing the note of the Prophet <hi>Dauid; O Lord I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the habitation of thine houſe, and the place where thine honour dwelleth:</hi> and another of the ſame, <hi>O Lord of Hoſtes, how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable are thy tabernacles! my ſoule longeth, yea euen fainteth, for the Courts of the Lord: my heart and my fleſh cryeth out for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD.</hi> Fiftly, I loue his<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 10.40.</note> meſſengers and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, the Preachers of his word, which are ſent vnto mee from God to treat about concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of peace, <hi>beſeeching
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:26211:62"/>
mee in Chriſts ſtead to bee reconciled to God. O how beautifull are the feete of him that bringeth theſe good tidings, that publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth peace, that bringeth good tidings of good, that publiſheth ſaluation to me!</hi> Sixtly, I long for the comming of Chriſt, not as though I could no longer beare (for impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie) the miſeries of this life (which are but light in compariſon of the weight of glory) but that I might bee married for euer vnto Chriſt, my Loue, in perfect ioy, and harts delight, being now
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:26211:63"/>
but eſpouſed onely to him, and that I might be perfectly freed from all ſinne (whereby I grieue both him and my ſelfe) and alwaies praiſe his name in heauen, <hi>How long Lord, how long?</hi> thou haſt<note n="d" place="margin">Re. 22.20</note> ſaid, <hi>Surely I come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Amen. Euen ſo come, Lord Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Thus it appears that the loue of God will warrant a man (as it doth you) no les than heauen: but what ſay you now of loue to Gods people? may not that bee ranked among the euidences of your ſaluation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:26211:63"/>
               <speaker>Conuert.</speaker>
               <p>Yes without doubt: For,<note place="margin">The tenth ſigne of ſaluation taken out of 1 Ioh 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>heereby we know</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Iohn) that he haue paſſed from death vnto life, becauſe we loue the brethren:</hi> theſe doe I loue, that is, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and ſuch as are godly, and theſe will I loue for euer; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that loue is ſuch a debt, as I ſhall be alwaies owing; and yet I muſt, and will bee euer paying; I will ſtriue to be rather a creditour, than a debtor heerin, and will not only returne to the Saints of God the loue of loue, the ſame meaſure that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:26211:64"/>
from them but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vſury and aduantage of loue: and I would to God there were as many paied vſe for loue, as doe in theſe dayes pay vſe for money. Then ſhould they be no whit impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, leſſe in the vſurers books, &amp; more in Gods: and ſo would it be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Whereas you ſay you loue the godly, it may be that is onely becauſe they are friendly to you, or becauſe you receiue, or hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, ſome outward kindnes and benefit from
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:26211:64"/>
ſome ſuch: if your loue be no other than this, it is but ſelfe-loue, beeing grounded meerely vpon your owne priuate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie: and this kinde of loue may bee found in an vnregenerate and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>It is not ſo with me: for (though happily I may regard ſome ſuch for ſome ſuch reſpects as you name, yet if I ſhould not loue the child of God for his own ſake, and for his and my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake, more than I loue my worldly friend for my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities ſake;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:26211:65"/>
or my kinſman for neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bloud, I ſhould bee void of any ſparke of true heauenly loue: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I chiefly loue the godly for their goodnes and godlineſſe ſake: the ground of my loue vnto them, is the image of god in them. This is that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine load-ſtone, which drawes my affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>How can you make it appeare, that you loue them with a right affection?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Thus: 1. becauſe I loue ſome ſuch in the<note n="*" place="margin">In ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracto.</note> abſtract, euen when
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:26211:65"/>
they are ſeuered and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from all externall reſpects and grounds of loue to mee-ward: as,<note place="margin">4 Notes of true loue to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> when I heare or reade of the zeale, piety, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, heauenly vertues, and gracious endeauours, of the worthy ſeruants of God, ſuch as I neuer knew, nor had any dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with; yet I finde, that I loue them, and feele the affection of my heart ſpreading it ſelfe towards them, to embrace them: which cannot be for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reſpects, nor worldly hopes, for it may bee ſome of them are dead,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:26211:66"/>
and gone, and thus I loue the Saints departed, which are now in heau'n: ſometimes alſo I haue knowne and loued ſome worthy Chriſtians, who then haue flowed with worldly proſperity, but after haue fallen to a very low ebbe of great aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: when the world hath bidde them, adieu, &amp; friends, wealth, goods, haue altogether taken their leaues; yet then haue I loued them as dearely as euer I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: whereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that my loue was not grounded vpon
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:26211:66"/>
worldly regards, which all forſooke them, but vpon their goodnes and godlines which ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I much affect the godly, and delight exceedingly in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, yea of ſuch as are nothing of kin vnto mee, that<note n="e" place="margin">Ro. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>wee may bee edified, through our mutual faith;</hi> whereas I care not for the company of others wanting true godlineſſe, though they may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes of my very neere kindred. So that I can truely ſay,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſa. 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>As for the Saints that are in the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:26211:67"/>
earth, and the excellent, in them is all my delight:</hi> but as for others, <hi>I haue hated the aſſembly of euill doers, and will not ſit with the wicked:</hi> and if of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I bee forced to bee in their company, then am I readie to wiſh with the Prophet, O that I had wings lik a Doue, then would I flie away, and be at reſt: or if this (ô) will not ſet mee at libertie, then I take vp <hi>woe</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my miſery, <hi>Woe is me that I ſoiourne in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar.</hi> 3. I haue a fellow-feeling of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:26211:67"/>
miſeries of the Saints, my deare Chriſtian brethren and ſiſters: which works in mee compaſſion, and makes my heart euen ake and bowels yearn within me; to ſee their grief, and behold them in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Whereby I perceiue, that I haue the true affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: <hi>for, if one member ſuffer, all the members ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with it.</hi> Fourthly, I finde in mee a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in ſome meaſure, to impart my ſelfe vnto them, in life and goods, ſoule and bodie, ſo far as I canne to affoord them
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:26211:68"/>
helpe and ſuccour: for, as it is truely ſaid of faith that<note n="*" place="margin">Fides toto copulatiua.</note> it is wholly copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue, wholly employed in coupling vs to Chriſt; ſo may it as truly bee ſaid of loue, that it is<note n="*" place="margin">Charitas communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catius.</note> wholly communicate, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in imparting it ſelfe, and what it hath, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for their good. Faith is as the leads, and pipes to bring in: and loue is as the cock of the conduit to let out. Now for as much as my loue is thus communicatiue to the children of God, becauſe they are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, heereby I alſo ſee,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:26211:68"/>
that it is of the right kinde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Alledge ſome other ſure ſigne of your ſaluation. For, the more, the better man: the richer you are in the true trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the more comfort may you haue thereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>fulfill the deſire of them that feare him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth ſign of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taken out of Pſal. 145.19.</note> &amp; that <hi>he wil heare their cry, and will ſaue them.</hi> Now I finde in ſome meaſure in mee the true feare of God: and though I ſay not of my ſelfe, as the Scripture ſaith of <hi>Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah,</hi> that<note n="g" place="margin">1 Kings 18.3.</note> 
                  <hi>hee feared God
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:26211:69"/>
greatly:</hi> yet this I can ſay, that I deſire to feare God greatly; and this I dare ſay in deſpight of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, that I feare GOD truely. Therefore I ſhall be ſaued certainly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods holy word of truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. IOHN telles vs, that <hi>there is no feare in loue, but that perfect loue caſteth out feare.</hi> Seeing then you loue God, how can you bee ſaid to feare him? how can theſe two ſtand peaceably toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Very well: for, there is a two-fold feare
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:26211:69"/>
of God: the firſt is a ſlauiſh and ſeruile feare, in horrour to dread his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, as a ſeuere reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Iudge, eyther execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his iudgements, or readie to take vengeance on his enemies. Thus all impenitent perſons, and the Diuels feare him, and onely thus; and therefore hate him, wiſhing there were no God. And this is the meaning of <hi>Saint Iames,</hi> when hee ſaith,<note n="h" place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The Diuels beleeue, and tremble.</hi> The ſecond is a childe-like feare, in awe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reuerence, and loue toward God, to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:26211:70"/>
not to offend him: now this feare is the true &amp; naturall birth of loue; being bred and brought, forth of it. Looke then, as <hi>Sarah</hi> caſt out <hi>Iſmael,</hi> the ſeed of the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, but would not caſt out her owne deare ſonne <hi>Iſaac:</hi> euen ſo the loue of GOD doth caſt out of mee, by degrees the ſeed of bondage, the ſlauiſh feare, but not her owne birth, the awefull and holy feare of God: but cheriſheth and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth this continually in mee, and is as a nurſe vnto it; ſo that now I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:26211:70"/>
feare not ſo much that God will condemne me, as that I may not offend him ſo good ſo louing a father to mee: euen as a good ingenious childe feares to offend his father for very loue; but feares not that his father will cut his throat, or murder him, ſeeing hee knowes he loues him dearely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Many ſay they feare God, and yet doe but lye againſt the truth: how know you, that yours is this true childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like feare of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt (as I haue<note place="margin">6 Notes of the true feare of God.</note> ſaid) becauſe it followes
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:26211:71"/>
vpon the former ſigne of ſaluation; namely, the loue of GOD, and is an inſeparable companion thereof, as another <hi>Ruth</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Ruth 1.16.17.</note> hanging vpon her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Naomie:</hi> for, loue in feare, and feare in loue, is a ſound teſtimony of the true feare of GOD. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it worketh in me maruellous humiltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and cauſeth mee in awfull reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his glorious maieſtie, to abaſe my ſelf as ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full duſt and aſhes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his bleſſed preſence: as <hi>Iacobs</hi> feare of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau,</hi> made him
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:26211:71"/>
humble himſelfe, &amp;<note n="k" place="margin">Ge. 3.3.</note> bow to the ground 7. times before him. Thirdly, it makes mee afraid of ſin, &amp; to flee from it as<note n="l" place="margin">Exo 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> fled from his rod when it became a ſerpent: it makes me feare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne ſecretly, as well as openly (for, though no eye doe ſee me,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 16.8.</note> I ſet the Lord alwaies before me) as it kept<note n="n" place="margin">Ge. 39.9</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from committing foly, though hee might haue done it cloſely and couertly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Fourthly, it makes me hate ſinne: for,<note n="o" place="margin">Pr. 8.13.</note> 
                  <hi>The feare of the LORD</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) is to hate
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:26211:72"/>
euill,</hi> yea, inward corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which ſticke in the cranies of the ſoule, and cannot be deſcried, but but a very narrow ſearch; it cauſeth my heart to riſe vp againſt rebellious luſts, which lie lurking within: as, ſecret A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, pride, vaine-glory, hypocriſie, enuy, and the like. Fiftly, it makes mee<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>depart from euery euill way,</hi> and from iniquity, to breake off the practiſe of ſinne, in the courſe of my life; to be a diſcontinuer, in <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>way of ſinners,</hi> and a reſident in the paths of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:26211:72"/>
righteouſneſſe. Sixtly, this true feare of God diſpelleth (ſo farre as it preuaileth in me) all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe feares; as, feare of men, of pouerty, of diſgrace, of death, &amp;c: whereas men voide of the feare of God, are full of fond, and fooliſh feares; they feare the croſſing of an Hare, the howling of a Dog, the crying of a Rauen, Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yea fancies, and their owne ſhadowes: as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wicked man may iuſtly feare euery thing, becauſe hee feares not God; ſo contrariwiſe,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:26211:73"/>
the righteous man needs fear nothing elſe, becauſe hee feares him. This one thing then wil I fear, that I may feare nothing but GOD: and that I may rightly feare him, <hi>O knit my heart</hi> ſo neer <hi>vnto thee O Lord, that I may feare thy Name:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad to ſee you ſo well ſtored of this diuine grace and rare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, the fear of God: oh, I would many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands had more of this good ware in their ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, their hearts. But how elſe are you aſſured, that you ſhall be ſaued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:26211:73"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord of his goodnes hath giuen mee to taſte of the firſt fruits of the heauenly Canaan, already, as a pledge of the plenarie poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of heereafter: he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me that ſpiritual ioy, which is a heauen vpon earth. And like as the<note n="r" place="margin">Num. 13.23.</note> cluſter of grapes broght from the Brooke Eſhcol, with other fruits, was an Earneſt to Iſrael of the future inheriting of the earthly Canaan: euen ſo is this ioy to me, of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting that goodly, that heauenly Land (whereof this is ſome of the right
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:26211:74"/>
fruit) the kingdome of glory:<note place="margin">The twelfth ſigne of Saluation taken out of 1 Pet. 1.8.9.</note> and I can bring <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peter</hi> to be bound for my truth in this point; for thus hee ſpeakes of them that <hi>reioyce with</hi> this <hi>ioy vnſpeakable, and full of glory,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>receiue the end of their faith, euen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>True Ioy (I hold well) is a good pledge of heauen: but how proue you, that yours is true ioy? for who ſeeme more merry, more frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, or iocund, than ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, worldly, yea vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men? they ſeeme
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:26211:74"/>
to haue as light hearts as any; and indeed, in my iudgement, too light to be poized, and ſettled, with the weight of grace; in a word, too light to be good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Well haue you ſaid, that they ſeeme ſo ioyfull; and now haue you ſpoken the beſt you can of them: for indeed they ſeeme, and doe but onely ſeeme ſo: their ioy is like the laughing of a man in his ſleepe, who dreaming of ſome very pleaſing delights, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in his imagination thereat, but when hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:26211:75"/>
hee findeth no ſuch cauſe: euen ſuch is the ioy of the wicked; they doe but laugh in their ſleep, and the diuell ſhall giue them ſuch a greeting and good-mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row one day, as ſhall make it manifeſt. And therefore well ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> of ſuch,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pr. 14.13</note> 
                  <hi>Euen in laughter the heart is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, and the end of that mirth is heauineſſe.</hi> Now therfore,<note place="margin">6 Notes of the true ioy.</note> that mine is not this baſe-borne ioy, but of a nobler deſcent, but ſound and good, I proue it thus: 1. Becauſe ſhee is an hand-maide to the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:26211:75"/>
right noble and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Lady, Faith: ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goes alone, but is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies following her. For firſt, I beleeue through faith, that I am reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to GOD, and then heereupon I reioyce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus at peace with him: and for this cauſe it is called,<note n="t" place="margin">Phi. 1.25</note> 
                  <hi>the ioy of Faith.</hi> 2. It iſſueth out of the right veyne and fountaine: it ſpringeth out of the bitter root of godly ſorrow, and griefe of heart for ſinne: neither can any come to drinke of this water of life, this heauenly Ioy, till they
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:26211:76"/>
haue firſt drunke of the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> bitter yet godly ſorrow; as our Sauiour tells his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>your ſorrow ſhall bee turned into ioy.</hi> 3. It is faſtned vpon the right obiects: for I chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in heauenly and ſpirituall things, as in God himſelfe; I can ſay with the Prophet, He is<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 43.4.</note> 
                  <hi>my exceeding ioy,</hi> and<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 4.7</note> 
                  <hi>Lord lift vp: the light of thy countenance vpon me, hereby thou haſt put glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in my heart!</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce alſo in the word of God, <hi>as one that findeth a great ſpoile,</hi> yea <hi>it is the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:26211:76"/>
very</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 15.16</note> 
                  <hi>ioy and reioycing of my heart;</hi> yea then when it ſearcheth me euen to the quicke, herein I finde an hony-combe. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the grace of God wrought in me, and others, as alſo in my own and their<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 51.12</note> ſaluation; <hi>I reioyce in the</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 5.2</note> 
                  <hi>hope of the glory of God,</hi> in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vſe<note n="b" place="margin">2 Chro. 30.21.</note> of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, in prayer, chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian conference, in Pſalmes, and ſpirituall ſongs, making melodie to the Lord. <hi>I am glad when they ſay vnto me, let vs goe into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> I reioyce in the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:26211:77"/>
welfare of Sion: <hi>yea, I can prefer Ieruſalem aboue my chiefe ioy.</hi> 4. It is <hi>the fruit of</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ga. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit;</hi> not of the fleſh, as carnall ioy is, which cauſeth men to reioyce onely or chiefly in their corne and their wine, their wealth and their honours, their pleaſures and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; this, nature affords vnto them. But I finde in me a ſupernaturall ioy, in things diuine and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; which, corrupt nature can take no liking of, much leſſe delight therein: therefore it hath been wrought in me by a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:26211:77"/>
power diuine, that is the fruit of Gods holy ſpirit. 5. Whereas the ioy of the wicked is ſlight and ſhort, a flaſh and away, no better then the chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of birds in a ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine day: mine is firme, and durable; not like ſummer-fruit, which holds good but for a time, for the ſummer-ſeaſon of proſperity: but my ioy is laſting fruit, which ſtill holds good; yea, euen in the hardeſt winter of greateſt aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,<note place="margin">Ro. 5.3.</note> I can <hi>ioy in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi> 6. It is a victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ioy: for, when as
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:26211:78"/>
griefe like lead lies heauy on my heart, preſſing it downe, then doth this ioy lift vp my heart in faith, together with my hands, eyes, and voyce vpward to the heauens, <hi>aboue the mountaines, from whence my helpe commeth;</hi> wherby appeares, it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth griefe, and getteth victorie ouer ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: thus I haue that which is the very life of life, true ioy: for life without this, is hardly worthy the name of life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>This pawne of heauen, which the Lord
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:26211:78"/>
hath put into your heart, I may not, nor cannot except againſt: therefore proceed vnto another ſigne of your ſalution.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Patience vnder the croſſe may not bee left out nor forgotten, no more then it may bee caſt off, or forgone; well it deſerues a roome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong this good compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of witneſſes, all which giue in euidence, that heauen is mine.<note place="margin">The thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth ſine of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on taken out of Iam. 1.12.</note> That this is a ſure ſigne of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>S. Iames</hi> proues it, when he ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation, for when he is
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:26211:79"/>
tryed, hee ſhall receiue the crowne of life:</hi> and that it is in me; my conſcience proues it; therefore I am bleſſed: but more bleſſed ſhall I bee when I receiue the crowne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Well may the crowne indeed be ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of patience, ſo noble, and ſo conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a grace: for, chriſtian<note n="*" place="margin">Nobile vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus eſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia: vincit qui patitur.</note> ſuffring is a noble kinde of conquering; and hee that ſo ſuffereth, no leſſe than conquereth. And if you haue alſo found this gemme in you, happy are you, prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that it be true pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:26211:79"/>
how prooue you that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">5. Notes of true pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</note> Becauſe I doe not onely finde out, but alſo finde fault with any inclination or diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion toward impatiency: I check and controul my ſelfe for it: when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſtirre, I begin to ſtifle it before it gather ſtrength, or get to head. 2. I doe not goe about to preſcribe to GOD the meaſure of afflicting me; nor yet the manner, meanes, or time of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, eaſing, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mee: I can bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the grace of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:26211:80"/>
God in the forgiueneſſe of my ſinne, and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Spirit, tho I want other things; and can receiue the loue of God with good content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though it come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or attended with the croſſe. 3. I more feare to doe the euill of ſinne, than to ſuffer the euill of puniſhment for ſinne,<note n="*" place="margin">Malum parti malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non eſt: malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facere malum eſt.</note> for, to ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is not euill, but to commit ſinne is euill: and I can be content ſtill to beare the puniſhment, ſo that the ſinne may bee taken away; oh, I would not for any thing that
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:26211:80"/>
the rod of God ſhould be remoued, before the Cure bee throughly wrought. 4. My pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence goes accompanied with a profiting vnder the correcting hand of God: for firſt it <hi>brings forth</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.4</note> 
                  <hi>experience,</hi> both of the care, and loue, and gracious dealing of God towards me, as alſo of my owne eſtate and cariage toward him; and thus I come to haue better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, &amp; with my ſelfe: it alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth my loue toward him, &amp; makes me cleaue and cling faſter to him, as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:26211:81"/>
a childe doth to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, when hee turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from it, and maketh as though he would goe away, and leaue it to the wolfe: it ſtrengtheneth my faith, and cauſeth me to relie more ſtedfaſtly on God, in diſtreſſes for time to come, and a dram of tried faith is better then a pound of vntried. Laſtly, it worketh in me reformation: I am not like wicked <hi>AhaZ,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">2 Chr. 28 22.</note> who <hi>in the time of his diſtreſſe, did yet treſpaſse more and more againſt the Lord.</hi> For I can truely ſay with the holy Prophet,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 119.67.</note> 
                  <hi>Before I
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:26211:81"/>
was afflicted, I went aſtray: but now haue I kept thy word</hi> ô God. Thus by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience I reforme my ſelf; and thus <hi>in patience I poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſse</hi> my ſoule: therefore it is true patience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>By what other certain ſigne are you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of your euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſaluation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>They which haue receiued the <hi>Earneſt of the Spirit in</hi> their <hi>hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth ſigne of ſaluation taken out of 2. Cor. 1.22 Eph. 4.30. Ro. 8.16.17.</note> are thereby <hi>ſealed vnto the day of redemption:</hi> this haue I receiued, to wit, the infallible teſtimony of GOD's holy ſpirit, which beareth witneſſe
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:26211:82"/>
with my ſpirit, that I am the child of God, and ſo an heyre of glory: ſeeing <hi>God (who cannot lye)</hi> tels me by his ſpirit, I ſhall be ſaued, I hold it (as I am bound) for a neceſſary, and a moſt vndoubted truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Thouſands of vngodly ones, haue a perſwaſion, that they ſhall be ſaued, and none ſeeme more confident than they, and yet it is but preſumption, and the illuſion of the deuill in them; for they haue no more true right to ſaluation, than <hi>dogges</hi> to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:26211:82"/>
the <hi>childrens bread:</hi> yea, and though they ſweare to it too (as, that they are ready enough to doe) yet you neede not credit them, vnleſſe you will; and if you doe, it is but a lye: as if a woman that had a child, ſhould ſwear ſhe were a maid; or one that had a plague-ſore on him, ſhould ſweare, that hee were cleere; would you beleeue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, for all their facing of the matter? ſure you would not: how know you then, that yours is the teſtimony of Gods Spirit, and not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:26211:83"/>
preſumption, which is nothing elſe but the lying ſpirit of Sathan in the mouth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and hearts of all his children?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conuer.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5. Notes of the true teſtimony Gods of ſpirit.</note>Firſt I proue it by the birth of it: for it hath been wrought and planted in me, <hi>contrary to nature,</hi> by the word of God, heard, read, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated vpon, and the like good meanes: whereas preſumption, like a ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weed, growes of it owne accord, out of the ranke ſoyle of Nature. 2. As <hi>Iacob</hi> may bee knowne by <hi>Iacobs</hi> voyce, from <hi>Eſau:</hi> ſo may this
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:26211:83"/>
be knowne by its voice; for it doth not barely tell mee, I ſhall be ſaued, but proues it to me, and perſwades mee by all theſe former ſignes which I haue alledged, and diuers others: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as preſumption doth only ſuggeſt that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit vnto men, but proues it not; ſo that when they are asked, why they thinke, they ſhall bee ſaued, they are not able to alleage any ſound ſufficient reaſon for the ſame. 3. The witnes within me ſpeaks the ſame, that the word
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:26211:84"/>
of God doth without me, both being the voice of the ſelf-ſame ſpirit of God, which cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it ſelfe; but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous preſumption, ſpeakes contrary to Gods word: for whereas the Scripture ſaith,<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 18.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnleſſe a man bee conuerted, hee cannot enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God:</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9</note> 
                  <hi>the vnrighteous ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the kingdome of God:</hi> and<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> 
                  <hi>without holineſſe, no man ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> and that the Lord will <hi>take</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>vengeance on them that know him not, and obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:26211:84"/>
Chriſt:</hi> yet preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beares men in han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, they ſhall be ſaued how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, and is ready to buzze into their eares, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alas good Sir, <hi>pitie your ſelfe,</hi> theſe things <hi>ſhall not bee vnto you.</hi> 4. Gods ſpirit, doth as well<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 8.27.</note> make interceſſion for mee, as witnes to me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brings mee to God, making me pray earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and feruently to him from a ſenſe and feeling of my manifold ſinnes, with groanings, which cannot be vttered: but preſumption driues men further from God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:26211:85"/>
worketh any ſuch feruent prayer in them. 5. Gods ſpirit brings forth the fruits of the Spirit in mee, as loue, ioy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentlenes, goodnes, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. whereas pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, as it is of the fleſh, ſo it yeelds the fruits of the fleſh, as adultery, fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, wantonneſſe, hatred, variance, wrath, ſtrife, enuyings, murders, drunkenneſſe, reuellings, and ſuch like, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. and theſe are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fruits of theſe daies, which grow more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb facs="tcp:26211:85"/>
in townes and houſes, then crabs doe in woods, and hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes: They which bring forth ſuch fruits as theſe, giue heede to the witch that ſpeakes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them; the ſpirit of Sathan, who tells them, they ſhall bee ſaued as as ſoone as the beſt, and they beleeue him: but I will heare what God the Lord will ſpeake; for hee will <hi>ſpeake peace vnto his people, and to his Saints:</hi> Yea, O Lord, let mee heare this thy voyce within mee, ſpeake low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I may heare
<pb facs="tcp:26211:86"/>
thee better, <hi>O ſay vnto my ſoule, I am, thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>There may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as manifeſt a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the lying ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Diuell (to ſuch as are not wilfully blinde) as is betweene light and darkneſſe; truth and falſhood: But leſt I be burdenſome to you, name one ſigne more of your ſaluation, and that ſhall ſuffice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>It is no whit irkeſome to the men of this world to looke on
<pb facs="tcp:26211:86"/>
their gold and ſiluer, their deedes and leaſes; nay, they take a meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light therein: why then ſhould it be burdenſome to the children of God, to view, and looke ouer the markes of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſeeing theſe are much more precious then gold that periſheth? But for as much as you require but one ſigne more, I will endeauor to comprehend all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one: In ſumme then; I perceiue that I am one of thoſe, whom God hath faithfully promiſed
<pb facs="tcp:26211:87"/>
in his word to ſaue:<note place="margin">The fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth ſigne of ſaluation.</note> for though a number of men, yea, the greateſt number thinke to get heauen, though they haue neither ſcrip, nor ſcrole to ſhew for it: yet I haue both Gods word and his writing to ſhew; or rather his word in writing, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen belongs to me. Now the Scripture is a true copie, and draught of the booke of life, taken out of the court of heauen by Gods owne hand, ſo that there can be no er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in it: Hereby I know that my name is written
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:26211:87"/>
in the booke of life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I finde my ſelfe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roled in Gods holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, among thoſe, to whom he hath promiſed eternall life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede If you be of that number, there is no doubt, but you ſhall be ſaued: For<note n="n" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>he abideth faithfull, hee cannot deny himſelfe:</hi> but are you ſure, that you are ſuch a one?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Though all that I haue hitherto ſaid, and the ſignes which I haue produced, drawne out of Scripture, and grounded thereon, doe
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:26211:88"/>
verifie the ſame, yet (if you will giue mee leaue) I will further proue it by other expreſſe texts of Scripture (though the ſame for the moſt part in ſubſtance, with that I haue already ſaid) that as you haue ſeene my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall euidences, truely taken out of the graund copie, ſo now you may alſo ſee the grand copy it ſelfe: <hi>in the volume of which book I finde it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of me,</hi> and that in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places, that I ſhall bee ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>This would I gladly ſee: proceed then to ſhew it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26211:88"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>God in his word hath promiſed, that<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 34.8.</note> 
                  <hi>hee will bee nigh vnto them, that are of a broken heart, and that hee will ſaue ſuch as hee of a contrite ſpirit,</hi> he himſelfe hath vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the cure of ſuch,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 147</note> 
                  <hi>Hee healeth thoſe that are broken in heart, and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp their wounds</hi> (as it is in the Pſalme) and a wonderfull cure indeede he will work vpon them: euen then when all helps do vtterly giue them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; hee, like the good Samaritane, will binde vp their wounds, and poure in the oile of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:26211:89"/>
and wine of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; hee will take them in his armes and bring them<note n="q" place="margin">Can. 1.4</note> 
                  <hi>into his Chambers,</hi> hee will take the care of them, and worke the cure on them, for none can doe it but hee, none can cure throughly the heart-wound, and ſuch as are ſicke thereof, but onely God: Such a one am I; I am bruiſed, and broken in heart, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and diſtreſſed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for my ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and wretchedneſſe; hauing by my ſinnes (O my ſins) ſo many, great, and grieuous, deſerued
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:26211:89"/>
no leſſe then the heauy wrath of God: <hi>O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee</hi> from ſin; that vnwelcome gueſt; nay, that deadly enemy? <hi>I thanke my God through Christ,</hi> for by him I haue deliuerance: Oh ſtill vouchſafe, deere God, to viſite mee, thy poore patient; and though I be not worthy, with the Centurion, that thou ſhouldſt come vnder my Roofe, yet farre bee it from mee, to ſay as <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Luk. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord depart from mee, for I am a ſinful man;</hi> nay, rather therefore come to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:26211:90"/>
me, for I haue the more neede of thee; <hi>the whole neede not the Phyſition, but the ſicke,</hi> as I am: thou lookeſt for ſuch a Patient, ſweet Ieſus, and I lacke ſuch a Phyſition as thou art, Oh bee pleaſed to come home vnto mee, poure forth ſome more of thy precious oyle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my wounded heart; Oh ſpread a plaiſter of thine owne heart blood, and apply it to my ſoule,<note n="r" place="margin">Can. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Stay me with thy flagons, and comfort mee with thy apples, for I am ſick of loue:</hi> My heart is wounded within mee, but ſeeing
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:26211:90"/>
thou haſt promiſed, I know thou wilt performe it; that thou wilt cure mee; that thou wilt ſaue me, being thus perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my ſoule for my ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How elſe can you proue your ſelfe to bee ſuch a one as God hath promiſed to ſaue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to<note n="t" place="margin">Re. 21.6.</note> 
                  <hi>giue to him that is athirſt, of the fountaine of the water of life freely,</hi> that is, hee which ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſires the fauour of God, through Chriſts righteouſneſſe, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting of eternall life,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:26211:91"/>
ſhall bee aſſured thereof, to the allaying of the ſcalding heat of his boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling conſcience, and to the endleſſe comfort and ſaluation of his ſoule: thus I doe thirſt, I doe no leſſe truely then earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire ſaluation.<note place="margin">3 Notes of the true deſire of ſaluation.</note> Firſt, in the right place, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it before all things in the world. Secondly, to the right end, that I might bee wholly freed from ſinne, and perfectly glorifie God in Heauen. And thirdly, in the right manner, as well deſiring the meanes that leade therto, as the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:26211:91"/>
they leade. Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it is, that the more grace I receiue, the more I hunger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſuch a ſpirituall drought and vnſatiable thirſt after Chriſts moſt precious bloud and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſneſſe, that my ſinfull ſoule may bee clothed with this fine white garment and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous attire; and oh how I long after the fauour of God: and like as the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſaid vnto our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our (when hee told them of the bread of Heauen);<note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 6.34</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, euermore giue vs
<pb facs="tcp:26211:92"/>
this bread:</hi> ſo I, hauing taſted the ſweetneſſe of Gods fauour, cannot chooſe but pray, Lord, giue me euermore to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy this thy fauour: yea <hi>Euen as the Hart panteth after the water brookes; ſo panteth my ſoule after thee O God, my ſoule thirſteth for God, for the liuing God, like to the thirsty Land.</hi> Well, yet his word is good,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſ. 107.</note> 
                  <hi>hee ſatiſfieth the longing ſoule, and filleth the hungry ſoule with goodneſſe; and this is my comfort.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Whom elſe hath God promiſed to ſaue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:26211:92"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 5.3 1.</note>
                  <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>are the poore in ſpirit, for theirs is the Kingdome of heauen:</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted:</hi> Theſe poore ones, and theſe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are they which are humble &amp; lowly in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſeeing &amp; feeling their ſpirituall wants, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, their ſinnes and miſery, being heartily ſorry for, and bewailing the ſame; and ſo deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as touching any goodneſſe of their owne, betake themſelues whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the mercy of God
<pb facs="tcp:26211:93"/>
in Chriſt: which mercy of God is like the<note n="y" place="margin">Act. 3.2.</note> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull gate of the temple, whereat poore creeples lye, yea lazers, a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of impotent folke, blinde, halt, withered, ſpirituall beggers, wofull creatures, poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, humble crauing an almes at the hand of ſo pitifull a God. And well doth Gods mercy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to bee called the beautifull gate of heauen, for heereby onely doe penitent ſinners enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of God, <hi>to behold the beauty of the Lord,</hi> and to enioy his
<pb facs="tcp:26211:93"/>
bleſſed viſion for euer in heauen. Thus doe a poore creature, lye day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at Gods beautifull gate knocking, crauing, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 57. &amp; 51. &amp; 86.</note> 
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpon me, O God, haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, according to the multitude of thy compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons put away my iniquities, incline thine eare, O Lord, &amp; heare me, for I am poore and needy; O bow downe thine eare and heare, open thine eyes and ſee, for my heart is ſmitten and withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red like graſſe, and I am in great miſery,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 25.16. &amp;. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>O turne thy face vnto mee and haue mercy vpon mee, for I am
<pb facs="tcp:26211:94"/>
deſolate and afflicted, looke vpon my affliction, and my paine, and forgiue all my ſinnes: O turne vnto mee, and haue mercy vpon mee, heale my ſoule, for I haue ſinned againſt thee,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 9.19.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord heare, O Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, O Lord, hearken and doe, deferre not for thine owne ſake, O my God.</hi> Thus am I poore in ſpirit, and thus doe I mourne, and therefore the promiſe of bleſſedneſſe belongs to mee, and I haue as good right vnto it as any poore ſinner whatſoeuer, for the poorer the ſinner is in ſpirit, and the greater
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:26211:94"/>
begger hee is, the better right he hath heereunto; ſo then, I am bleſſed (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts owne words) becauſe I ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Whom elſe hath God ſaid he will ſaue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ro. 10.13</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall call vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall bee ſaued,</hi> as witneſſeth the Apoſtle: that is, whoſoeuer not onely in outward miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but alſo and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in ſpirituall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, ſhall pray vnto the Lord in faith, both as concerning his power, and will to helpe, and
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:26211:95"/>
and yet more, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fearing that hee hath not faith, nor any ſauing grace, that he is not in the fauour of God; nor his ſinnes pardoned, and that his ſoule ſhall not bee ſaued, if hee can but finde a heart to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for theſe things with an honeſt &amp; vpright minde; as ſure as the Lord is true, he ſhall bee ſaued, and that by vertue of this promiſe of God; <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall call vpon his name, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued;</hi> for thus he flyeth vnto this ſtrong Tower, where hee ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:26211:95"/>
ſerued ſafe a while, and after ſhall be remooued by the guard of good Angels to the Palace of None-ſuch in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, which is a priueleged place; where ſinne; Sathan, the fleſh, and the world, haue nothing to doe and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall not bee there moleſted by any of them in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Now I am one of them that doe thus call vpon the name of the Lord, and that dayly, when I feele my ſelfe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and can finde very
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:26211:96"/>
ſmall, or (to my thinking ſometimes) no grace at all in mee, yet then can I heartily pray vnto the Lord, for his helpe and ſauing grace that I may be ſaued, therefore I ſhall bee ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>To whom elſe hath God promiſed ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in his word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; that<note n="e" place="margin">Reu. 3.21</note> 
                  <hi>hee which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer commeth, ſhall ſit with him in his Throne,</hi> that is, hee that holds out to the end, continually reſiſting and fighting againſt his ſpirituall enemies, the world, the fleſh and the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:26211:96"/>
Diuel, ſhall haue (though not equall glory) yet fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Chriſt in glory euerlaſting: thus do I daily fight that I may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome: Firſt, I account my ſelfe a ſpirituall ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, bound &amp; ſworn to my Captaine the Lord Ieſus, of whom I haue alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken preſſe-mony, the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and weare his colours, the profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and know there is martiall Law, eternall death for mee, if I ſhould flye from my Captaine. Secondly, I take notice of the manifold traines,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:26211:97"/>
and plots of my forreign enemies, the world and the Diuell, and the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and treacheries of my domeſticke foes; the fleſh, that Rebell, my headſtrong paſſions and vnruly luſts, thoſe tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: I ſee and obſerue, how they euery where lay ſnares for mee, <hi>and ſpread nettes in my path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ſet grinnes for me, purpoſing to cauſe my ſteps to ſlide,</hi> and to ouerthrow my ſoule, theſe do I ſee; whereas men of the world ſee no ſuch ſnares laid in their wayes by their ſpirituall enemies,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:26211:97"/>
for the entrapping of their ſoules, &amp; the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering thereof; for aske them, and they cannot tell you of any, but are like <hi>Samſon</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Iudg 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.20.21.</note> their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are vpon them, and they faſt a ſleep in carnall ſecurity, and ſo the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell preuailes againſt them, puts out their eies, and leades them captiues at his pleaſure, hee makes a mocke of them; and makes ſport with them, but at length hee falls from ieſting and brings them to deſtruction in good earneſt. Thirdly, whereas theſe my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:26211:98"/>
doe continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege mee, ſeeking to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade mee, I therefore keepe daily watch and ward, fortifying in this my little Kingdome, the City of my ſoule, and Caſtle of my heart, I haue a ſpeciall care, to looke well to the gates and cinqueports, my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes, whereby oftentimes diuers traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thoughts and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious luſts, are ready to ſteale in, which cauſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often much mutinie, in the ſoules common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, for if I ſhould grant liberty for ſinne
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:26211:98"/>
to breake in, the diuell would enter too with his great Armado of his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſpirits, and would take poſſeſſion, placing his deputies in ſtrongeſt holds, as the ſpirit of blindneſſe in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; of error in the iudgement, of lying and ſlumber in the conſcience, of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hardneſſe in the heart, and ſo in the reſt: Thus with his Legions would hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-runne mee deſolate. Fourthly, I reſolue when I am in the conflict, with
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:26211:99"/>
the allurements of the world, the inticements of ſinne, the temptations of Sathan,<note n="*" place="margin">Imperato rem opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet mori ſtantem, <hi>ſaid Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tian; ſo,</hi> Chriſtianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> militante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>may we ſay.</hi>
                  </note> rather to die, then to yeeld to any of them, I purpoſe neuer to giue ouer fighting, as long as I haue any breath within mee: not doubting but I ſhall at length haue perfect vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, onely through the might of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theneth mee. <hi>Fight thou O God, againſt them that fight againſt me, and ſtand vp for my helpe, through thee I ſhall doe vallantly, for thou ſhalt tread downe
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:26211:99"/>
my enemies, and bruiſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than vnder my feet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Who elſe ſhall bee ſaued according to the tenure of the records of holy writ?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Such as are<note n="g" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.21.</note> 
                  <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pollutions of prophane ones, and are <hi>ſanctified,</hi> are <hi>veſſells vnto honour:</hi> that is, they which are made parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of true grace; and ſo haue the Image of God renewed in them,<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 4.24</note> 
                  <hi>which conſiſteth in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and true Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> ſhall bee heyres of glory, theſe are they which are called Saints:
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:26211:100"/>
Yea, the Lord himſelfe, that high and mighty. Potentate, is their God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, for he hath giuen them this name, what mortall man then dares bee ſo bold, as to nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name them with tearmes of reproach; or to finde fault with this name of Saints, which their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly God-father hath giuen vnto them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks none ſhould dare once to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call theſe, or to deny them their names, ſaying we cannot bee Saints heere, but let them goe: What is true ſanctifying grace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:26211:100"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>A new created quallitie of holineſſe, throughout the<note n="i" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.23.</note> whole man, <hi>in ſpirit, ſoule, and bodie,</hi> that is, in minde, will, and all our bodily members; yea, in all the powers of the ſoule, and parts of the bodie, wrought in vs by Gods ſpirit, for the honouring of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Haue you this new qualitie of holineſſe in you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>I dare not denie but God of his mercy, hath begun this worke of grace in ſome weak mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in mee: for how
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:26211:101"/>
could I poſſibly bee thankfull to the Lord, for ſuch an ineſtimable gift, if I ſhould not take notice of it, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it; eſpecially conſidering that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry leaſt meaſure of ſauing grace that can be, is farre more worth, than I can expreſſe, or praiſe God for enough, ſo long as I liue: deny it therefore I dare not, (though it bee very ſmall) leaſt I ſhould bee vnthankfull to the Lord, for ſo great a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the leſt ſeede of grace is: but this I dare doe, to pray to him for
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:26211:101"/>
more: yea, and I beſeech him to make me <hi>rich in all grace,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Ph. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>filled with the fruits of righteouſnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his glory and praiſe;</hi> for he alone is<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> 
                  <hi>able to build mee vp further, and to giue</hi> mee <hi>an inheritance among all them which are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It appeares by all theſe ſignes which you haue produced, that your aſſurance is not that common counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit ware which goes for currant among a number of men, a vaine fleeting conceit in the braine, but that you are truly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:26211:102"/>
of your ſaluation: I muſt confeſſe, I can no way miſlike theſe your euidences, hauing thus examined them, nor (I thinke) a whole councell of Diuines, if they ſhould ſit to determine thereon. I cannot ſee, how any can pick a hole, or finde a flaw herein: &amp; I iudge, that you haue as good a title to Heauen, by theſe your Scripture euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the beſt landed man in the world hath, or can haue, to his beſt freehold, by his parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment euidences: But I pray you; now tell mee
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:26211:102"/>
further, are you not ſomtimes troubled with feare, and doubting of your ſaluation, for all this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Oh alas; good ſir, I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that I am, and that not a little to my griefe. I am none of thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident fooles, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doubted in all their liues, whereby they giue euidence againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they neuer yet beleeued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>But how then;<note place="margin">To ſtriue againſt doubting: diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> do you not ſtriue againſt doubting, as being a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euill and permicious thing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:26211:103"/>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, that I doe: for to yeelde vnto that, were to entertaine Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than for my counceller, who is my greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſay, and to take him for my chirurgian, to heale my wounded hart, who is my deadlieſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy: no, Sathan ſhall not be my chirurgian; for in ſtead of healing the wounds of my heart, hee will make himſelfe more worke, hee will make more ſores, then hee heales: and thoſe which hee ſeemes to heale, hee doth but skin ouer, with the ſtinking ſalue of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood:
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:26211:103"/>
and the wounds which are, hee will make deeper and more incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let all good people take heede of this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering chirurgian. I haue experience enough of him, &amp; therefore though hee doe impudently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude his ſalue vnto mee, yet I caſt it away from me, that is I ſtriue againſt doubting, with all my might and power; as one would worke againſt the pangs of death, to retain life and breath: and I am bound in conſcience ſo to doe, becauſe I know, (for as much as I haue
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:26211:104"/>
the true ſignes of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in mee) doubting proceeds from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Sathan, who meanes me no good, and from vnbeleefe of heart in me, and is much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to my ſoules comfort, it is alſo greatly diſhonourable to God, for as a man hurts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt by preſuming, ſo he offers God the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt wrong, by doubting, indeed a double wrong: Firſt, hee offends his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice by ſinning; then he wrongs his mercy; by doubting of forgiuenes; yea, a triple wrong: for it
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:26211:104"/>
is to call his truth alſo into queſtion, and to make him a lyer: for,<note n="l" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>He that beleueth not God, hath made him a lyar, becauſe he beleeueth not the record. that he gaue of his ſonne,</hi> as ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and doubting<note n="m" place="margin">Ro. 4.20</note> is not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: It is alſo great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to God, for he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands to beleeue,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>This is his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that wee beleeue in the name of his ſone Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> in regard of theſe infinite iniuries of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to God; hereby, it muſt needes be much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to him, and if I
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:26211:105"/>
were cleare of all other ſinnes in the world, yet I ſhould deſerue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, for this very ſin, if I did not beleeeue: Therefore it ſtands mee highly vpon, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand doubting, in all theſe reſpects, and not to liſten to thoſe ſecret que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, which Sathan pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds inwardly vnto mee by way of doubts, leſt by conſulting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, I ſhould be enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as <hi>Eue</hi> was: for firſt hee did but propound a queſtion to her, wherein one would thinke there were no harme,<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 3.1</note> 
                  <hi>Hath
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:26211:105"/>
God ſaid, Ye ſhall not eate of euery Tree of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den:</hi> But while ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to thinke of this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, hee wound further into her, and made her doubt of the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and at length grew ſo ſtrong, as that hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her, ſhee might eate thereof, and that it would be greatly for her good, and aduancement; this his olde policie hee hath not forgotten, but vſeth at this day, and therefore firſt propounds ſecret queſtions inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the minds of Gods children; ſuch queſtions,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:26211:106"/>
as ſeeme, in ſhew, not hurtfull, but profitable, that wee may know our eſtate better, as whether the promiſes belong to vs? whether God will keepe his promiſe with vs ſeeing wee breake our promiſe and couenant toward him? whether we haue faith? whether grace were euer ſoundly wrought in vs? (though we haue had experience thereof formerly) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we do not preſume? whether God will ſaue ſuch vnworthy ones as we are? &amp;c. which when we begin to thinke vpon,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:26211:106"/>
hee drawes vs to doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the truth thereof;<note place="margin">Not to liſten to Sathan by doubting.</note> and at laſt gets head, and growes ſo ſtrong, as that we are ready to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by him, that it is as hee ſuggeſts. Thus we often mak our ſelues worke, and puzzle our ſelues very much, by conſulting with Sathan: for the greateſt adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage wee haue againſt ſinne and temptation, is at the firſt; then it is weakeſt: but by, Demurre, it ſtill growes ſtronger, and gets ground of vs, and winds further into vs, by inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation. Therefore it is
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:26211:107"/>
wiſedome, to watch our time and take our aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; to refuſe diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when hee firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds his queſtion: for hee is to ſubtle a ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for vs to diſpute with. This therefore wee muſt do; wee muſt hold the concluſion in deſpite of all Sathans premiſſes: and this indeede will weary him, much ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then the popiſh Round, <hi>I beleeue as the Church beleeueth, and the Church beleeueth, as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue:</hi> For he is as weary of this, as he is afraide of holy water, and all one.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:26211:107"/>
My reſolution therefore is this, alwaies to holde the concluſion; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once found in mee ſome ſure marke of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, neuer after to giue any entertainement to doubting; but ſo ſoon as euer it creepes into mee, preſently to exclude it as the meſſenger of Sathan; not once to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murre, or pauſe vpon it: for the leſſe; the better, and more ſafe it will bee for mee. Oh, that I could ſo doe, according as I doe reſolue: O Lord, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mee that I may ſo doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:26211:108"/>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed, the way to haue any ability here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, is to aske it of the Lord,<note n="p" place="margin">Iam. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Who giueth to all men liberally, and vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not:</hi> But acquaint mee (if you thinke good) more particularly, with ſome of thoſe things, which moſt, and ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt trouble the minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>To keepe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans counſell, is not, nor cannot bee good: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wil freely acquaint you with ſome of thoſe his policies, whereof I haue experience in my ſelfe. And firſt to begin at the very roote of all,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:26211:108"/>
namely,<note place="margin">Doubting of our ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> my election to ſaluation. Sometimes I beginne to doubt hereof, and to thinke that I am not one of the number of Gods elect; and that hee hath not decreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was, to ſaue me after the world ſhall be at an end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>That Sathan hath been heere, you may ſee by his footings. And as King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid to the ſubtle woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. 14 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Is not the hand of Ioab with thee in all this:</hi> So ſay I to you, hath not the ſubtle ſerpent had a hand with you in this? That he
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:26211:109"/>
hath, may appeare: for, he hath left, as it were, the print of his foule fingers behinde; and you may perceiue the clawes of this roaring Lyon, where he hath been ſcraping in the heart, to rake out of it, that aſſurance of your ſaluation, euen by the very roote, if poſſibly it might be. But tell mee: how doe you to foile this temptation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, I ſee vpon better thoughts, that there is no reaſon, why I ſhould lay blockes in my way: for, Sathan will lay enow to bring
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:26211:109"/>
me to eternall ruin, if hee can. And therefore, for mee to doubt of that whereof I haue no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to doubt, is againſt all reaſon. Secondly, I ſee it is an ouer-curious pride, for mee to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to prie into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and hidden councell of God, any other wiſe then as hee hath reuealed the ſame vnto mee: for, <hi>ſecret things belong to God, but things reuealed to vs.</hi> Therefore, thirdly, I learne by the word, (which is his reuealed will) that to bee truely called and conuerted<note n="r" place="margin">Ro. 8.30.</note>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:26211:110"/>
is a certaine declaration, that one is elected and predeſtinated to eternall life: for, thus <hi>the ſecret of the Lord is reuealed to them that feare him.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, finding my ſelfe conuerted, I thus reſt quiet in my minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>That the Diuell will lie ſhamefully, you ſee euidently; as, to tell you that you are not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, when it is more then he can tell, or all the men in the world beſide. Nay, you can tell him that it is a lie, for as much as you are conuerted: and ſeeing you haue thus
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:26211:110"/>
taken him in this lie, mee thinks you ſhould neuer belieue him more, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoere he ſaies. For, as this is not the firſt lie that he hath told, ſo it will not be the laſt, I warrant you. But tell mee: how elſe doth he aſſault you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>It is my great fault, I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, to giue ſo much credence to his lies, as I haue done: and that I haue ſmarted for tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, ere now. But to proceed further, he doth aſſault mee, by ſetting before mee my many wants and weakneſſes.
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:26211:111"/>
For,<note place="margin">Doubting becauſe of the wants &amp; weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of grace, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> I finde in mee, ſuch a poore and weake mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace, that at times I make queſtion, whether there bee any true grace at all in me: I haue not ſuch a feeling of faith as I deſire, nor of that ioy which at other times I haue felt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at my firſt conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I am alſo affraide, that I grieue not enough for my ſinnes; ſure I am, not ſo much as I would: which makes me doubt, whether theſe graces bee in me at all, and whether I were euer truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:26211:111"/>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How do you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercom this Diuell, when hee thus grapples with you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Thus I encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him: I remember what I haue learned, that they which ſee, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily bewail in themſelues the want of grace, cannot poſſibly bee without true grace: and the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth not ſo much the quantity of grace, as the quality thereof; not how much, but whether it bee of the right kinde: ſo that if it bee truely in mee, though but as a graine of muſtard-ſeed, it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb facs="tcp:26211:112"/>
with him. And as for feeling, it is no ſure rule to try my eſtate by: &amp; faith without feeling is ſtronger and more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then faith with fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. It was not ſo much<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 20.29</note> for <hi>Thomas</hi> to beleeue when hee ſaw and felt, as if hee had done neither. It is nothing for a childe, being dandled in the lap, to thinke his father loues him: but, when his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frownes and lowers vpon him, then to bee perſwaded of his loue, is ſomething indeed. And I ſtand bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as well to beleeue
<pb facs="tcp:26211:112"/>
when I want feeling, as when I haue it: for, Gods commandement of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, is not confined to the condition of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, experience, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: nay, he is the beſt ſcholar in Gods ſchoole, that reaſons leaſt vpon theſe grounds, and aſſents moſt. I muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeue, according to my feeling of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; but, muſt beleeue better, that I may feele more comfort. And as for my ioy, I call<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 77.6 Pſal. 143.5</note> to minde the comfortable experience that I haue had at times heeretofore
<pb facs="tcp:26211:113"/>
of my conuerſion, and the liuely feeling of grace working in mee, and that ſweet conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I haue had in the aſſurance of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, in former times. Heereby I relieue my ſelfe, and gather, that true grace is in mee, though at the preſent it doth not ſo cleerely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it ſelfe; for ioy is more perceiued of ſome at their firſt conuerſion, than euer after; but it is becauſe of the newneſſe, ſtrangeneſſe, and ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, which makes a deeper impreſſion, and
<pb facs="tcp:26211:113"/>
cauſeth greater admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for, it may bee more after: like as one, that is brought out of ſome deepe and darke dungeon, (wherein hee hath been encloſed all his life before) into the ſun-ſhine, more ioyes in it at his firſt comming forth, then after, when he hath been daily wonted to it, and yet may enioy more cleare and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome daies by farre, then at the firſt, and may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy alſo more conſtant and continuall comfort thereby; and like as a begger, that is aduanced
<pb facs="tcp:26211:114"/>
to ſome very great and vnexpected honor, ioyes more at the firſt therein, than afterward, and yet his dignities and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues may daily increaſe and grow farre greater than at the firſt; and like as the Ghurch at their firſt returne out of capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, had their<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 12 6 2.</note> 
                  <hi>mouth filled with laughter, and their tongue with ſinging,</hi> and yet inioyed more good and comfortable dayes after in the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſeruice and worſhip of God, then at their firſt returne. As touching my griefe for ſinne, though
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:26211:114"/>
it makes mee hang down my head to ſee the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> heart this way, and the ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine (for hee<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>made his bed to ſwimme, and watered his couch with his teares,</hi> and I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhed on teare for my fins (yet in that I am afraid, that I doe not grieue enough, yea, and therefore grieue becauſe I can grieue no more, it is heereby euident that I would faine grieue more; which the Lord accepts of: <hi>for if there be firſt a</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>willing minde, it is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to that a man
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:26211:115"/>
hath, and not according to that hee hath not:</hi> and ſecondly, though in the intention of my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Perk. Caſ. Con.</note> my ſorrow for ſinne ſeemes little, and leſſe then my ſorrow for worldly loſſes, yet in the eſtimation of my minde it is greater; becauſe I grieue for my ſinne, as the greateſt euill of all, and ſo in truth of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe account it; and grieue for the loſſe of Gods fauour, as for the loſſe of the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and excellent thing of all: and thus I ſee that my weakneſſe in grace,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:26211:115"/>
is no iuſt cauſe to make mee think that I haue no grace, no, not in the leaſt meaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further, to ſhew Satans cunning in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to vnſettle and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>The multitude, and greatneſſe of my ſinnes (which Sathan ſets before me) doe now and then much diſmay and affright me, and make me almoſt faint. I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 40.12.</note> 
                  <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable euils haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed mee about, mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities haue taken hold vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:26211:116"/>
mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doubting becauſe of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and greatneſſe of ſin, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo that I am not able to looke vp, they are more then ths hayres of my head, therefore my heart faileth mee.</hi> And beſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſinnes, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly much oppreſſed, with hardneſſe of heart, coldneſſe of good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, dulneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, barrenneſſe of good thoughts, motions and deſires, with manifold foule corruptions. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue alſo ſundry imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in my prayers, and in the beſt duties; ſo that when I looke backe on the ſeruice, which I performe to God, I finde
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:26211:116"/>
it ſuch ſimple, patched, and broken ſeruice, that I feare, leaſt hee ſhould account it vs ſinne vnto mee, and that it ſhould bee as abomination to him, and that hee ſhould abhorre both mee and it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How doe you beate backe this tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, for my ſins, I learn, and beleeue that God is able to forgiue my greateſt ſins, as well, as the leaſt; yea all, though bloody ſinnes,<note n="z" place="margin">Eſa. 1.16 18.</note> 
                  <hi>as red as ſcarlet,</hi> and though they be innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:26211:117"/>
for, his mercy far paſſeth my ſinnes, yea, the ſinnes of the whole world. <hi>Great is the Hell of my ſinnes</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>But greater is the depth of thy mercies, O Lord.</hi> This bottomleſſe deepe is not like<note n="a" place="margin">2 Kin. 19.24.</note> thoſe pooles about <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which might bee dried vp with the tramplings of horſe and horſemen; but ſuch as all the ſinnes of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds cannot drie vp.<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> I remember a ſpeech of an ancient Father to this purpoſe; who (vpon thoſe words of <hi>Cain, My ſinnes are greater then can
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:26211:117"/>
bee forgiuen</hi>) ſaith, <hi>Thou lyeſt Caine, the mercies of God are greater than the ſinnes of all the world;</hi> and no maruell: for, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God hath all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions. It is ſo deepe, that it brought vp <hi>Dauids</hi> ſoule from the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hell: it is ſo high, that<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 36.5.</note> it <hi>reacheth to the heauens:</hi> it is of ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable length &amp; bredth, that it<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 103.12.</note> 
                  <hi>remoueth our fins as farre from vs, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt.</hi> And the cauſe, why the ſinnes of all the world are not pardoned, is not becauſe Gods mercy cannot par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:26211:118"/>
them; but becauſe they cannot repent, that they might bee pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So then I make no doubt, but that God of his mercy is able to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue my ſinnes, bee they what they will bee; yea, and further, vpon my vnfained repentance hee will forgiue them; if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, he will forgiue: for wee cannot be ſo ſinfull; as hee will be mercifull, if for our ſinnes wee bee heartily ſorrowfull. For this hee hath promiſed; and by this his promiſe is become indebted to vs, whereas we onely by
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:26211:118"/>
our ſinnes, were debtors to him, ſo that now he is not only a mercifull cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor to vs, content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe the debts of our ſinnes; but alſo by his promiſe become our debtor, vpon our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to giue vs a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and vpon our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, to giue vs heauen; O vnſpeakable mercy! Well, ſure I am, he is a true debtor, and will pay what he hath vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; therefore I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, hee will forgiue my ſins: for ſeeing when hee knew all the ſinnes, that euer I ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:26211:119"/>
hee would notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in loue, ſend his ſonne to be my Sauiour; whereas he hath now by his death made full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for them, ſhall I thinke the Lord will ſtick at the pardon of them? Now as concerning the hardnes of my heart, I ſee, I neede the leſſe to feare it, in regard I haue a ſight, and ſenſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and vnfainedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the ſame. For like as it is with a greene wound, if it bleede well, when it is made, there is the leſſe feare of rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp; more good hope
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:26211:119"/>
of curing; ſo, for as much as I feele my heart bleed, in bewayling the hardnes of it, I ſee there is the leſſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of feſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring inwardly to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of my ſoule. For my weaknes in the ſeruice of God, though Sathan would hereby take occaſion to keep me from the word, prayer, and Sacraments (perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mee, that I doe but take the name of God in vaine, and prophane his worſhip, and increaſe my own condemnation) yet I am reſolued to try ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries with him, and not
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:26211:120"/>
to neglect Gods ſeruice, and theſe holy exerciſes at any hand; for if hee could once get mee at this bay, hee would tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph indeed: and I fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider to my comfort, that God mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth the obedience yeelded to him, rather by the<note n="*" place="margin">Deus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur affectu quam effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</note> deſire, and will to obey, than by the large and exact perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof. Though therefore I doe not all the good I would, yet ſeeing in loue, I deſire to doe it; and though I bee not wholly rid of all the euill I hate, yet ſeing in
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:26211:120"/>
hatred thereof, I deſire to be rid of it, God will accept of that which I doe, and will impute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>What is it elſe, that doth diſquiet your minde, and interrupt your peace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Sometimes I feare that all the grace which I haue conceiued to bee in me,<note place="margin">Doubting procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from fear of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie anſwered.</note> and all that I do at any time in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and worſhip of God, and the holineſſe which I make ſhew of, is but all in hypocriſie: which my conceit growes the
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:26211:121"/>
ſtronger on mee, becauſe I ſee ſometimes ſome who haue been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted very rare Chriſtians, farre excelling mee, in knowledge, ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeale, forwardneſſe, and other gifts, and yet haue fearefully fallen away from the grace of God, and ſo fowly diſcouered themſelues, that it hath appeared euidently, they neuer had the ſoundnes of grace in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>This is a ſlie temptation indeed; for thus the Diuell <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes himſelfe into an Angell of light,</hi> as though
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:26211:121"/>
hee loued ſincerity, and would haue men ſincere; whereas hee hates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while hee thus goes about to condemne you of hypocriſie, hee ſhewes himſelfe a damned hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite: but how deale you with this ſubtile ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, I ſee I haue no warrant to take ſo neere to heart, the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full examples of back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding hypocrites, as to queſtion mine owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate therefore: for tho ſome earthy comets, and muddie meteors are
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:26211:122"/>
drawne aloft ſometimes, and make a great blaze, than the true ſtarres of light, but after a ſhort time vaniſh away; yet the true ſtars muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor will not leaue their place, or ſhining: and though the wolues ſomtimes goe in ſheeps clothing,<note n="*" place="margin">Non debet ouis pellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuam depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, quod lupi aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſe ca co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Aug.</note> yet muſt not the ſheepe therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe their clothing, and thinke themſelues to bee wolues. Secondly, I conſider, that to ſee, feare, and ſhun hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, is to bee ſincere. Whiles then I feare it, I haue the leſſer cauſe to
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:26211:122"/>
feare the danger of it, and am the further from it. Thirdly, I deſire rather to be good, than to ſeem to be ſo; and to do good rather than to ſeeme to doe it: therefore I am not an hypocrite; for hee deſires the contrary, he lookes chiefly to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, I to the inſide, to my heart, I haue an eye to that to keepe it in good temper,<note place="margin">The good temper of the heart.</note> eſpecially in two reſpects, 1. Supple, and ſoluble, that is, alwaies humble, (for elſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee long in ſpirituall health) and 2. alwaies hungry, keeping in my
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:26211:123"/>
heart an appetite vnto Chriſt by faith, and vnto all good things in loue thereof: and for the maintaining of my heart in this good temper, I vſe a daily good diet of the ſoule, namely, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, meditation, prayer, reading, conference, &amp;c. I am chiefly deſirous and carefull to know how my eſtate indeed ſtands before God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take paines to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my ſelfe ſoundly, and throughly, and am very willing to bee tryed by others; this working thorow-ſtitch, the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:26211:123"/>
cannot brooke. 4. The hypocrite doth not vſe to goe to God in<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 6.5.6.</note> ſecret by prayer, (when hee thinks none knowes, ſees, or heares him) and that in conſcience being acquainted with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of his owne ſoule, and priuie to his owne corruptions, to bewaile them to God, and to cry for grace; but this I doe: neither yet would I haue once mentioned this my practice vnto you, (for feare of vaine-glory) but that I now ſtand vpon my triall, and muſt in this caſe produce all the
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:26211:124"/>
witneſſes I can. Fiftly, I finde in my ſelfe, that I ſhould bee full ſorie, that all ſhould be but in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in me: O, I would not for all the world it ſhould be ſo: yea, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire from my very heart, that it may be in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; hereby I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it is not in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, but in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well: how elſe doe you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this temptation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>I may perceiue in my greateſt feare and doubting, that ſome of the ſignes of ſaluation
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:26211:124"/>
are in me in truth: as firſt hatred of ſin, for though there were no hell (as I haue ſaid before) I would not commit thoſe ſinnes which ſome doe (though nature corrupt doe reliſh them very well) my ſoule goes againſt them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of leſſer ſinnes, (which the world count no ſins) as wel as of thoſe great and groſſe ſinnes, which ſtare vs in the face: and though ſome would ſhrinke vp ſinne into a narrow ſcantling, and faine would bring it to this, that none doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:26211:125"/>
but they which are in gaoles, yet I haue learned otherwiſe to iudge of ſinne, to<note n="e" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>abſtaine from all appearance of euill:</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it a point of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to looke to ſinne in time, leſt it feſter, and eat in, &amp; infect more, and at length breake forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a running ſore. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I loue the godly in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, not for feare of hell, (that cannot make mee loue them) nor for any ſiniſter reſpects, but becauſe they are godly. Fourthly, when I go to the word preached, ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, prayers, and all
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:26211:125"/>
other holy exerciſes of religion, I heartily deſire to vſe them, not for forme or cuſtome, (as the manner of moſt is) but with profit, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lift vp my heart to the Lord, crauing his bleſſing in the vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for the edifying of me in grace, and for the rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vp of my corrupt heart: an hypocrite doth nor thus. Fiftly, though the Lord ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne mee, (which hee neuer will) and throw mee into hell (which in regard of his faithfull promiſe hee neither will,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:26211:126"/>
nor can), yet I finde my heart ſo affected, that ſure I ſhould neuer blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his holy name with the Diuels and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits, but euen out of the bottome of the loweſt pit ſhould I praiſe him, yea, out of the very<note n="f" place="margin">Iona. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>bellie of hell</hi> (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ionah</hi> ſpeaketh) ſhould I pray vnto him: ſo that I ſee, I loue the honour of God, neither for feare nor fauour, but in ſincerity; whereby I alſo gather, and conclude that I am ſincere and not an hypocrite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Be there yet any
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:26211:126"/>
more euill ſpirits of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, ſent of him to vexe you, that put you in feare and would make you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue lies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, it is not for nothing that their name is <hi>Legion, for they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> there is another which doth not ſeldome moleſt me; for when I cannot deny (vpon a right tryall taken of my ſelfe) but that the grace of God, is in ſome meaſure begun in mee, yet then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſteps in a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe meſſenger of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,<note place="margin">Doubting of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> much like his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that hath ſorſworne
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:26211:127"/>
all ſhame &amp; truth, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to out-face mee, and beare me down by maine ſtrength, hee will needs face mee downe that I ſhall not continue in grace; the way to heauen ſo ſtraight and difficult, my skill ſo little, my weakneſſe ſo great, my enemies ſo many, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, crafty, reſolute and malicious, that it is not poſſible for mee to hold out to the end, that I might be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Dare you looke this Goliah in the face, or enter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat with him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, that I dare,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:26211:127"/>
and doe, and will doe all my dayes, becauſe hee blaſphemeth the liuing God, as though he could lye, or did repent; but <hi>I doe not truſt in my owne bow, neither can my ſword ſaue me:</hi> I do not betake my ſelfe to my owne ſtrength, good mind, and meaning, free-will, &amp;c (as blinde Papiſts and others doe) for theſe are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of Sathans owne making; and be ſure hee will make none to hurt himſelf withall: therefore I take vnto mee, <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 6.17</note> 
                  <hi>ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God;</hi> this
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:26211:128"/>
I brandiſh againſt the tempter, and tell him, as it tells me, that<note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 31.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the loue of God is an euerlaſting loue;</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>whom Chriſt loueth, hee loueth to the end;</hi> and<note n="k" place="margin">Io. 10.28.</note> 
                  <hi>none can plucke mee out of his hand,</hi> neither men nor diuels; and<note n="l" place="margin">Ro. 8.39.</note> 
                  <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſeparate mee from the loue of God in Chriſt,</hi> neither life, nor death, <hi>height nor depth, things preſent, nor things to come,</hi> no, not ſin it ſelfe, (which is moſt likely of any thing) for that lyes pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and waſting in mee, in as much at the firſt inſtant of conuerſion, it
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:26211:128"/>
fell into a deepe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and that incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, all the drugs of that old Empirick the Diuell, can neuer reſtore it to perfect ſtrength againe: therefore I ſhall endure to the end, and in the end bee ſaued, for all that. Secondly, for the better animating of me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere,<note n="m" place="margin">He. 12.2</note> 
                  <hi>I looke vnto Chriſt the author and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of my faith:</hi> he held out to the end in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for mee, why ſhould not I then hold out to- the end in ſeruing of him? he would not leaue me in hell fire, why then
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:26211:129"/>
ſhould I leaue him in the heat of temptation, or in the cold bleake winde of affliction: well, I am<note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>confident of this verie thing, that hee which hath begunne the good worke</hi> in me, <hi>will performe it vntill the day of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>What is there elſe, which doth perplex your minde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doubting of preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>I am now and then grieuouſly affraid, that I doe but preſume, in being perſwaded, that I ſhall be ſaued by Chriſt: partly, becauſe I am ſo very ſinfull, and my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:26211:129"/>
is ſo great; and partly, becauſe (mee thinks) I doe not grieue enough for my ſins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>What helpe do you vſe, againſt this ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, I conſider, that it is but ſpirituall pride, in the habite, and ſhew of great humility, to feare to beleeue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our great ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vnworthines; for thus wee ſhew wee would haue ſome thing of our owne to bring to God, or elſe we dare not truſt him: we would ſpie ſome righteouſneſſe and
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:26211:130"/>
worthines in our ſelues, before we bee perſwaded of ſaluation, and ſo not to be beholding to God: this proceeds from the poyſonfull root of pride, and naturall popiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of meriting at the hands of God. Secondly, I muſt not hang off from beleeuing, till I finde, that I grieue enough for my ſinnes: for this were to ſet the cart before the horſe. In as much as godly ſorrow for ſinne, proceeds from faith, therefore I muſt not ſtay to beleeue, till I finde more godly ſorrow, but
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:26211:130"/>
I muſt beleeue more, that I may grieue more for my ſinnes; for the more faith, the more godly ſorrow. Thirdly, indeed if I had bin neuer hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the fearefull ſight of my ſinnes, and a ſenſe of the heauy load there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then I ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, if I did perſwade my ſelfe in that eſtate to bee ſaued: but now I ſee, and feele my ſinnes, and miſery, and what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme neede I haue of Chriſt, God calls me as verily, as if it were by name, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. to come vnto Chriſt, that is,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:26211:131"/>
to beleeue in him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there can be no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in ſo doing, I can not ſinne, or preſume in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded that I ſhall bee ſaued by Chriſt: for that perſwaſion which followes ſound humiliation is faith; that which goes before is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. Therefore I may well be out of feare, that my beleeuing is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming; nay, I can not doe amiſſe in being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that I ſhall bee ſaued, I can not bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough herein: but this belongs not at all to them, that were neuer
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:26211:131"/>
troubled in minde, nor wounded in conſcience for the greatneſſe of their ſinnes, the dread of hell, and horrible wrath of God due to them for their ſinnes; for they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed preſume.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I like and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue well of this that you ſay; but let me heare if there bee any further matter, which cauſeth doubting in you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Euill thoughts,<note place="margin">Doubting becauſe of euill thoughts anſwered.</note> and cogitations, are no ſmall dauntment to me: for neuer was the land of Aegypt more peſtered with noyſome vermine,
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:26211:132"/>
than I am with foule, filthy, impious, yea, ſometimes blaſphemous thoughts againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maieſty of God, they come vpon me thicke and three-fold, I can at no time, in no place, be quiet for them; yea, when I am in the preſence of God, ſpeaking vnto him by prayer, or he ſpeaking to mee by his word, or when I am about any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy duty, euen then they come crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in vpon me, (I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſomtimes with my ſelfe, how, or which way they ſhould ſo creepe in)
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:26211:132"/>
to amaze, and aſtonie me, and withall to choke and interrupt the holy buſineſſe I haue in hand: the vglineſſe of theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thoughts, works hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and quaking in my heart, and makes mee thinke my ſelfe no better than a firebrand of hell, and that I might do well (O Lord, forgiue that horrible, and murdering thought) to make away my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>This ſeemes to bee as ſtrong a Diuell as any, that driues you thus neere the gates of death, (I had almoſt ſaid of
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:26211:133"/>
hell) how doe you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer ſtrength, and to get the victory ouer him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Strong hee is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but<note n="o" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.4</note> 
                  <hi>greater is hee that is in vs, than hee that is in the world.</hi> Firſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conſider, that I do not loue, like, and approue of theſe euill thoughts, wherewith I am ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, nay I abhor them, as the Diuell himſelf, (by whom they are hatched) inſomuch as they make mee euen weary of my ſelfe, becauſe of the ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breath thereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſteaming forth,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:26211:133"/>
ready almoſt to choake my ſoule: and when Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than by theſe thoughts, doth breake in violently vpon mee, I doe not bid him welcome, and lay him (as it were) a cuſhen, to take vp his ſeat in my minde, and heart, to haue reſidence in me, by theſe ſo vile and horrible mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and cogitations: but I deale by him, and them, as men doe by theeues, that breake into their houſes, at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, they giue them no abode, but hunt, and driue them out againe (ſo ſoone as euer they
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:26211:134"/>
come within the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold) with all the ſpeed &amp; power that they can: and therefore the Lord will not account mee a friend vnto them, much leſſe the father of them; I ſhall not beare their name, much leſſe the burden of them, he will neuer lay them to my charge, to anſwere for them. Secondly, I am reſolued, as long as I liue, (for ſo long I ſhall bee troubled with them) to reſiſt them with all my might. And like as<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 32.2 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> ceaſed not to wreſtle, though his thigh
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:26211:134"/>
was bruiſed, till hee had the bleſſing; ſo neither will I, till I haue got the victory. Thirdly, I know that the Lord will not be angry with mee, for theſe euill thoughts, which I conſent not to, nor take no pleaſure in, but hate: for will a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mother, bee angry with the babe ſhee beares in her armes, becauſe ſome naughty people fling ſtones at it, hurt it, and make it cry? nay, will not rather her bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els vern to ward it? will ſhee not rather hugge it cloſer to her, ſtroake it,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:26211:135"/>
kiſſe it, and bemoane it, but her anger is toward them that fling ſtones at it, whereby they bruiſed and battered the face of it, ſhe could finde in her heart to flie in their face, and to ſcratch out their eyes, that did her childe that harme: ſurely then the Lord will not bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with mee, becauſe my enemies, Sathan, and the fleſh, caſt fiery darts at mee, &amp; thereby wound mee; for I cannot helpe it: but his fierce indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is againſt them, for that they doe ſo moleſt me, and he doth, and will
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:26211:135"/>
both pitie, and helpe mee ſo much the more; for<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 103 13.</note> 
                  <hi>as a father pittieth his children, ſo the Lord pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth them that feare him:</hi> and his affection toward his children is infinitely farre ſurpaſſing the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the tender heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt mother in the world toward her deareſt babe; for <hi>though a mother could forget the childe of her wombe, yet would not I forget you, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Yet a litle more, I pray you let vs heare of Sathans deepe ſubtletie, and helliſh policie, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:26211:136"/>
to defeat you of all true comfort here, and of heauen it ſelfe heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doubting becauſe of afflictions anſwered.</note>Sometimes hee would needs perſwade mee, (and my owne heart withall is ouer-greedy, I confeſſe, to catch vp and ſwallow ſuch poyſoned morſels) that I am none of Gods children, and that the Lord doth not loue mee, becauſe I am kept ſo neere and bare, and am ſo followed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with afflictions. I am hardly free at any time from one or other; they are like <hi>Iobs</hi> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:26211:136"/>
while one is ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, before he hath done his meſſage fully, there comes in another, ſicknes, paines, aches, loſſes of friends, goods, good name; outward croſſes and calamities in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, beſide the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affliction of the minde; oh That the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of all, for <hi>a wounded ſpirit who can beare:</hi> a rare thing it is not to ſee mee vnder ſome one or other of theſe, to keepe me downe: whereas I ſee the wicked wallow in their wealth, as they doe in their wickedneſſe, and
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:26211:137"/>
                  <hi>Eſaus portion is</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 27.39.</note> 
                  <hi>the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the earth;</hi> they ſwim vp to the chin, in riuers of oyle, and <hi>waſh their paths with butter,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iob. 21.24. &amp; 15.27.</note> 
                  <hi>their breaſts are full of milke, and their bones run full of marrow:</hi> their <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are couered with fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and they <hi>haue col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops in their flanke:</hi> yea,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 73.7.</note> 
                  <hi>their eyes ſtand out for fatneſſe, and they haue more than heart can wiſh:</hi> yea,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſ. 119.70.</note> 
                  <hi>their</hi> very <hi>heart is fat as greaſe:</hi> they are ſo fat, <hi>ſo luſty and ſtrong,</hi> that they kicke vp their heeles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their keeper, and will not know their daily
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:26211:137"/>
benefactor, but contemne their maſter:<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 21.14.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſay to God, depart from vs, for wee deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes. Beholde theſe are the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, who proſper in the world, they increaſe in riches:</hi> but as for mee, poore wretch,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 73 14.12.</note> 
                  <hi>all the day long haue I beene puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and chaſtened euery morning:</hi> heereupon <hi>my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well nigh ſlipt;</hi> for I began to thinke that theſe were Gods dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, at leſt my ſelfe none of Gods beloued ones; for <hi>the rod of God
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:26211:138"/>
is not on them,</hi> but neuer off from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>What meanes doe you vſe, to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued againſt the violence of this aſſault?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>I preſently take ſanctuary, and ſo am ſafe, <hi>I</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 73.17</note> 
                  <hi>goe into the Sanctuary of God,</hi> (and conſult with his word) <hi>and then I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their end:</hi> I ſee a man may goe through a faire City to execution; and contrariwiſe, through a narrow ſtumbling lane to a feaſt or coronation; I ſee well why it is that the wicked doe ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and fare ſo well, for
<pb facs="tcp:26211:138"/>
why doe men ſet vp their Oxen a-fatting? is it not againſt the day of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? ſo the<note n="z" place="margin">Iob. 21.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Wicked are reſerued to the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, they ſhall bee brought forth vnto the day of wrath:</hi> the ſeruants of God are kept at hard commons, but they haue their keeping of free coſt: <hi>the wicked, which are ſtrangers from the wombe,</hi> and none of Gods houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, haue larger cates, and farre better, but they ſhall pay ſweetly for it in the end, when the reckoning comes: ſo that all things conſidered, I
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:26211:139"/>
ſee ſmall reaſon why I ſhould heaw a ſtumbling-blocke out of the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the wicked, to my owne ouerthrow. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I labour in time of affliction, to ſpie out the loue of God ſhining vnto mee through ſome little peep-hole or other: at length I finde that euen then I loue God; heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I diſcerne that hee loues mee, for ſo he ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 8.17</note> 
                  <hi>I loue them that loue mee;</hi> and indeede, his loue to mee is the cauſe of my loue to him, ſo that it is impoſſible for mee to loue him in the time of
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:26211:139"/>
my affliction; but hee muſt needs loue mee much more. Thirdly, I conſider, that it is for want of wit in a childe, to thinke that his father cannot abide him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, when need is, hee vſeth the rod to correct him: for they which are of diſcretion can tell, that the father loues the child neuer the worſe for all that, but the better; yea, this very dealing of God towards mee, is an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token of his loue vnto mee, for<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 12.6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>whom the Lord loueth hee chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth euery ſonne
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:26211:140"/>
whom hee receiueth, if therefore wee endure cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening, God dealeth with vs as with ſonnes; for what ſonne is hee whom the father chaſteneth not?</hi> So that the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me with fire in the one hand, &amp; water in the other; the fire of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to melt out the droſſe of my corruptions, and the cooling water of comfort and aſſurance of his fauour, to allay the heate thereof, leſt I ſhould bee ouermolten with heauineſſe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: but indeed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he holds this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb facs="tcp:26211:140"/>
him, that I ſee it not, but I muſt not bee ſo vnwiſe as to thinke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee it not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee hath it not: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee not his loue, or at leaſt not ſo as I would, that therefore he loues mee not, farre bee it from mee ſo to thinke, though I am too ready ſo to thinke in my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe: but it is my infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. For as verily as he doth afflict mee, and I feele it; ſo certainly doth hee loue mee, though I feele it not. Fourthly, I conſider that this is the cup<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26.39. &amp; 27.46.</note> which Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:26211:141"/>
dranke of, hee drank it off to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, which made him cry out of the bitterneſſe of it, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> whereas I doe but drinke a littie of the vppermoſt: but ſeeing Chriſt my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath begun to mee therein,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 20.23.</note> needs muſt <hi>I</hi> pledge him, though it be but to kiſſe the cup: which is alſo a cup of Gods owne tempreing, and therefore very good and wholſome, though not ſo toothſome, hee knowes all the ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents perfectly that go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:26211:141"/>
it, and there is not one drop or dram of bitter aloes in it, more than hee ſees muſt needs bee put in, or elſe it would do vs no good: which alſo is skilfully corrected and ſweetely qualified with thoſe heauenly ſweets that farre ſurpaſſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and the hony-combe, as peace of conſcience, tranquilty of minde, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and ioy of each a dramme, and the hope of heauen, a maruelous ſweet thing, which it ſelfe alone (mee thinks) might well allay the tartneſſe and ſharpneſſe of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb facs="tcp:26211:142"/>
this is my comfort in time of griefe, my friend in time of neede, my beſt Phiſicke in time of ſickneſſe, and preſent remedy againſt all mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and I dare vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, that one dramme of this, well taken of a ſicke man, ſhall doe him more good at heart, than twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pounds-worth of the moſt precious Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries ſtuffe. O, it is a moſt ſoueraigne reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and happy is he that is neuer without ſome of it in his heart. It is of ſuch ſingular vſe at all times, and vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
<pb facs="tcp:26211:142"/>
Now ſeeing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are thus ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vs: properlie to ſpeake, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue no worſer name, than bitter-ſweets, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee reſpect inward diſtreſſes, or outward ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities: truth indeed the Lord layes more vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome, than hee doth vpon others, and more vpon vs, at one time, than he doth at an other: hee ſometimes ſtrikes an heart-veyne, when an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not ſerue, and that wee cannot bleede well at it, with godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; yet this I dare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch,
<pb facs="tcp:26211:143"/>
hee neuer puts vs to more paine, than needs muſt for our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and benefit. Fiftly, I enter into ſerious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the manifold good, which commeth by affliction, according to that of the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> 
                  <hi>It is good for me, that I haue been afflicted:</hi> this is the phyſicke that God doth miniſter to his ſeruants, and it is both purging phiſicke, and ſtrengthning phyſicke: for the former of theſe, it pleaſes the Lord here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſometimes to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and bring to our ſight
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:26211:143"/>
the diſeaſe of ſome ſinne, wherewith wee are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, whereof wee had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no notice before; and then to bring vs to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for it, ſo to worke the remoueall thereof: ſometimes hee doth hereby preuent ſome ſinne; whereto hee ſees vs very ſubiect, by purging out the ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of ſelf loue, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, pride, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſſe, which elſe, in time would break forth, into dangerous, yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diſeaſes: and thus he works a miracle vpon vs, turning the ſerpent,
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:26211:144"/>
ſinne, into the rod of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, as<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 4.4</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> his rod was turned: alas, how ready are wee to run out at randome after theſe earthlie things, to ſet our affections too much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and to be taken vp too much with them, to grow not onely wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, but euen wilde with the things here below? and how eaſie a matter is it for a man, to loſe both himſelfe, and heauen too, in running vp and downe in the maze of this ſinfull world? which that we may not doe, the Lord that good Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:26211:144"/>
vſeth his<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> rod, and ſtaffe: when wee ſtraggle too farre on the pleaſant green paſtures of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaines and pleaſures, hee fetcheth vs in againe; then hee begins to ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſhackle vs, with ſundry croſſes, to keepe vs better within compas, to make vs minde home better, and to make vs better husbands for our ſoules, that ſo wee may thinke of him in time of aduerſity, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgotten him in time of proſperity: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee ſees that wee truſt to the arme of fleſh,
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:26211:145"/>
and leane too much to ſome outward meanes, then by a croſſe he takes it away, that ſo wee might wholly and onely relie on him. Manifold corruptions, and much filth of ſinne doe wee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by walking in this dirty world: the Lord doth vſe the waters of affliction, as a bath to cleanſe &amp; purge vs from thoſe corruptions, in bringing vs thereby to a ſight thereof, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for the ſame: in theſe &amp; the like reſpects, well may affliction bee tearmed Gods purging
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:26211:145"/>
phyſicke. Sometimes he alſo vſeth it for ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning phyſick, when as he doth afflict his ſeruants for their triall, for the ſtrengthning of their faith, patience, loue, zeale, holy deſires, &amp;c. for theſe, and the like graces, the more they are exerciſed, the more they are confimed, and the ſtronger they grow: and euen inward afflictions of the minde, ſerue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to theſe good ends. O bleſſed rod of God, that doſt ſo much good! Did I thinke the Lord loued mee not, becauſe his rod
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:26211:146"/>
lay on mee! oh how could I bee without it? Surely it is as needfull for mee as my meat and drinke, and much more needfull too.<note n="*" place="margin">Hic vre, his ſeca, vt in aeternum pareas do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Aug.</note> O ſcourge mee, and launce me here, O Lord, that thou maieſt ſpare mee for euermore hereafter. Sixtly, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching outward calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I haue learned at length, a little wiſedome, by Gods word, for the right demeaning of my ſelfe therein; not to looke downeward, on the ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and roaring ſtreames of miſeries and troubles, which run ſo ſwiftly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:26211:146"/>
mee; for then I ſhould bee taken with a giddineſſe in the head, which would make mee thinke, and ſpeake an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly of Gods dealing, and my owne eſtate, and ſo I ſhould bee in hazard of being drowned and ouerwhelmed therein: but this I doe, I faſten my eies vpon the ſure ſtay, by which I am vpheld, that is, <hi>God all-ſufficient;</hi> and ſtedfaſtly behold his promiſe in the middeſt of all miſeries: thus (I praiſe God) I paſſe ouer many a dangerous deep,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 42.6.</note> 
                  <hi>when one deepe calleth
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:26211:147"/>
another, or the noiſe of the water-ſpouts,</hi> when one trouble comes on the necke of another, I paſſe ouer, or wade through, ſafe &amp; ſound. Seuenthlie, as I deſire to prepare for affliction before it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; ſo do I reſolue in like manner aforehand, to hold faſt my aſſurance of the loue of God, and ſo to beare it as comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably as may bee, when it ſhall come; obſeruing that it is the work of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; to make mee vtterly diſcomfortable in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; that heauen our country, and holineſſe,
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:26211:147"/>
the way thereto, might both be brought out of credit by my meanes; that others, beholding my vncomfortablenes, might bee diſcouraged from entring, or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the happy way to life. By the grace of God, Sathan ſhall not make mee his ſcar-crow, in the way to heauen, to keep others out, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by my ſweet and lightſome deportment of my ſelfe therein, I will allure others, what I may, rather to chooſe the way of the croſſe, the way to the kingdome,
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:26211:148"/>
than for fear of the croſſe, to loſe, and forgoe the kingdome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It is a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: and ſurelie it is not for any ill-will, that the Lord corrects his children, whether with inward afflictions of minde, or outward of bodie, friends, children, goods, good name; or howſoeuer elſe, his loue is neuer the leſſe vnto them, and he is neuer the further from them; and though they greatly feare ſometimes, yet they haue no more cauſe to feare, than the Diſciples
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:26211:148"/>
had, when Chriſt came walking to them vpon the ſea, thinking that they had ſeen a ſpirit; to whom our Sauiour anſwered,<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 14 26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee of good cheere, it is I, bee not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid:</hi> euen ſo when the raging windes and bluſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtormes of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe cauſe an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in our hearts, the Lord ſends forth a calme quiet voyce, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his children, <hi>It is I, bee not affraid;</hi> which all they may eaſilie heare, that will but lay their eare to the word of God, and liſten thereunto; for
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:26211:149"/>
ſo hee ſpeakes vnto them therein. Now if there be any other matter that troubles your minde, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it if you will for concluſion of all, leſt I bee alſo one of them that trouble you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doubting procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from feare of death an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>Why then, if you thinke good, wee will end with that, that ſhall end our liues, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, death: I greatly feare ſometimes that I am not as I ſhould bee, becauſe I finde in my ſelfe ſuch ſtrugling w<hi rend="sup">ith</hi> the thoghts of death, and that I am ſo affraid, yea and vnwilling to die.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="279" facs="tcp:26211:149"/>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How do you to repell, and ouercome this aſſault?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, I conſider, that they which are truly in Chriſt by faith, and liuing members of him, may haue, and haue all of them, ſome feare of death for all that, though it can do them no harm; like as man that ſeeth the ſting of a ſerpent plucked out before his eyes, &amp; therefore knowes it can not hurt him, yet hath ſome fearefulneſſe in him to handle it, and put it into his boſome, becauſe of that naturall
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:26211:150"/>
enmitie, and antipathie, that is between him and it: <hi>the ſting of death is ſinne,</hi> which Chriſt hath pluckt out, in <hi>being made ſinne for vs,</hi> and ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully for it, ſo that well may we ſay, <hi>O death where is thy ſting;</hi> and yet we are affraid of the very lookes of death, but more affraid to come nigh it, becauſe wee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally hate death: this therefore is no good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to make mee thinke my ſelfe none of Chriſts, becauſe I haue ſome feare of death; no more than it is to proue a man, no
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:26211:150"/>
man, or reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe hee is loth to put a ſnake in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, when the ſting is pluckt out. Secondlie, I take vp ſuch meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may make mee better and more famil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly acquainted with death, and may make mee better conceited of it, and to take better li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to it: as firſt, that it is the common lot of<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> none exempted, no, not the Worthies of the world, and holie Patriarcks; and ſhould I then deſire to
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:26211:151"/>
bee exempted? Death hath his warrant to take hold of euery ſinner; therefore none can bee ſpared, for <hi>all haue ſinned;</hi> but before hee comes himſelfe, hee ſends forth many ſummons to warne men to appeare at Court before God: euery ache, paine, ſicknes, faintneſſe, wearineſſe, yea, euery wrinkle, or gray haire, or dead coarſe, is deaths ſummons, to warne vs appearance; but becauſe we are too regardleſſe, &amp; make too light hereof, at length hee comes perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, with a ſpecial Writ
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:26211:151"/>
from the moſt high, and mighty Monarch of all the world, with a <hi>Capias corpus,</hi> firſt for one, and then for another, and at laſt for vs all. Now whereas, becauſe of this neceſſitie of death, many take care how to doe when death comes, I will chiefly take care how to doe before it comes: for if I liue well, I ſhall bee ſure to die well; this ſhall bee therefore my chiefeſt care, how to liue well. Againe, I labour to pluck away that grim, and gaſtly vizard of the curſe, which death hath
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:26211:152"/>
vpon it, and to looke at it through Chriſt, and then behold it hath a louelie countenance, and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke, ready prepared as the groome of Gods chamber, kindly to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace mee, and to bring mee into Gods preſence: and what is death elſe to the faithfull, but as<note n="e" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.15</note> 
                  <hi>the valley of Achor, the doore of hope,</hi> to giue entrance to their ſoules into the paradiſe of God, where are ioyes vnſpeakeable, rauiſhing the heart, and pleaſures at his right hand for euermore? and what is the graue but a
<pb facs="tcp:26211:152"/>
mould, wherein the Lord doth caſt our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into a new forme, making them incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, which before were corruptible? ſo<note n="m" place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>changing our vile bodies, that they may bee faſhioned like the glorious bodie of his Sonne.</hi> What is life but a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome way, and death to the godly a comfortable home? ſhould the faint, and weary traueller, bee loth to draw neere home? What is life but a toilſome labour, and death to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, a ſweet reſt &amp; ſleep? ſhould reſt be vnaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:26211:153"/>
or ſleepe vnwelcome to a toyled labourer? What is that which doth diſrobe the faithfull of all the baſe ragges of ſinne and miſery, and clothes them with the moſt ſumptuous garments of perfect righteouſneſſe, glory, and immortality? is it not death? Who would not be contented to bee ſtripped naked of beggerly robes, that ſo hee might be apparelled with gorgeous attire? Thus then, though I ſee ſome reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s why I might deſire to liue long, yet I ſee more reaſons why I
<pb facs="tcp:26211:153"/>
might much better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to dye ſoone; but none at all, why I ſhould bee vnwilling to die,<note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>To bee preſent with the Lord:</hi> for, <hi>whilſt wee are at home in the body,</hi> wee are abſent from him, and as it were in priſon. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the priſon of the ſoule, and the earth of the body: as wee muſt not breake priſon (for that is greatly diſpleaſing to the Lord); ſo when the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doore is ſet open to vs by authority (as when death is ſent vnto vs, hee comes with authority) wee ſhould very gladly,
<pb facs="tcp:26211:154"/>
and willingly depart, yea, and go forth ſinging with old father <hi>Simeon,</hi> (a <hi>Nunc dimittis</hi>)<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 2.29</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace.</hi> Vpon theſe and the like medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of death, I find in my ſelfe ſome willingnes to die: and that I may be ſtill more willing, I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to haue my thoughts more and more taken vp therewith, and at leaſt once a day to looke him in the face, that I may be ſtill better acquainted with him: for the more acquaintence I haue with death, the more friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:26211:154"/>
ſhall I finde at his hands, when hee comes to apprehend mee? and on whom doth hee: looke ſo ſowre and grimme, as on them that are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him, and hee to them? and as euery day I hold it a point of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to get ſome further acquaintance with death; ſo eſpecially vpon the occaſion of ſickneſſe; for euery ſickneſſe is a little death. I therefore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ſo to dye often, by making good vſe of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit of ſickneſſe, that I may once at the laſt dye well: that ſo, when my
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:26211:155"/>
departing ſhall come, it may bee a ſweet and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifice to the Lord: whether it bee a burnt offering, by the violent death of martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or at leaſt a peace-offering, by a naturall death, I deſire that it may bee a free-will offering, not wrung from me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, but freely ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>into</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the hands of a God, a faithfull Creator:</hi> and if my life be willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered, (which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire from my heart it may bee, and therefore know it ſhall bee) then ſhall it bee well and fauourably
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:26211:155"/>
accepted; for,<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 116.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the Death of his Saints.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord hath giuen you good wiſdome to diſcouer, and put to flight, theſe forces, and aſſaults of Sathan the deadly enemy of all the ſeede of man, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of <hi>the ſeede of the woman,</hi> the Church, <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.17. I ſee you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with ſome good skill, to diſpell the groſſe thicke clouds of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby the Diuell laboureth to ouer-caſt your euidences, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhould not ſee
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:26211:156"/>
them at all, or elſe very dimly, with little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>thanks therefore bee vnto God for this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable gift:</hi> but what if you could finde none of the ſignes of ſaluation in you at all, which you haue alledged to mee; how then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Time was when I had not any one of them, and then I was in the eſtate of damnation, though I thought my ſelfe in as good an eſtate as the beſt, and the diuell then perſwaded mee ſo too, (though ſince hee hath changed his note;
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:26211:156"/>
for hee muſt needs goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, or elſe hee is not himſelfe) yet ſince I ſee, that if I had died in that eſtate, I had without all faile gone headlong into hell: and in the ſelfe-ſame caſe are all they, which haue none of thoſe ſignes in them. <hi>S. Peter</hi> puts a queſtion to them, which puts all ſuch to ſilence, and makes them ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe now, but what will it doe hereafter then?<note n="r" place="margin">1 Pet. 4 18.</note> 
                  <hi>where ſhall the vngodly, and</hi> impenitent <hi>ſinner appeare?</hi> let the braueſt minde, the proudeſt, the
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:26211:157"/>
ſtouteſt ſtomacke of them all anſwer it if hee can: alas, alas, poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, they can none of them anſwer it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>They which haue not one of the ſignes of ſaluation in them, are in a wo-caſe indeed: but what if a man can finde but one ſigne in him, and not all?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>He that can finde but one of theſe true ſignes in him, hath cauſe of comfort; for though there bee but one good apple growing vpon a tree, it proues both that there is life in that tree,
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:26211:157"/>
and that it is not a choke-peare, or crab-ſtocke, but a good tree: but in truth, where there is one of theſe ſignes of ſaluation in a man, there they are all in ſome poore mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, though hee doe not ſo ſenſibly, and euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue all alike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It reioyceth me not a little to finde you ſo well prouided for the Lord; oh happy eſtate that you are in: for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now can come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe vnto you, come life, come death, you are the Lords. <hi>Now our Lord Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, and
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:26211:158"/>
God, euen our Father, which hath loued vs, and hath giuen vs euerlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, comfort your heart, and ſtabliſh you in euery good word, and worke, and preſerue you to that inheritance, which is incorruptible, reſerued in heauen for vs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo Lord Ieſus. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb n="297" facs="tcp:26211:158"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 32.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
Be glad in the Lord, and reioyce, yee righteous: and ſhout for ioy, all yee that are vpright in heart.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 1.4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The vngodly are not ſo: but are like the chaffe which the wind driueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>Therefore the vngodly ſhall not ſtand in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor ſinners in the congregation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:26211:159" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
